<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The freeness of the grace and love of God to believers discovered in reference to 1. their services and suffering, 2. their consolations, and 3. their salvation and eternal glory : together with the excellency of the fear of God, the goodness and pleasantness of brotherly love, the wisdom of hearing the voice of the rod, repentance the only way to prevent judgements / delivered in several sermons by the late reverend and faithful minister of Christ, Mr. William Bridg ...</title>
            <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19668</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258689</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57690</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29368)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57690)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 172:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The freeness of the grace and love of God to believers discovered in reference to 1. their services and suffering, 2. their consolations, and 3. their salvation and eternal glory : together with the excellency of the fear of God, the goodness and pleasantness of brotherly love, the wisdom of hearing the voice of the rod, repentance the only way to prevent judgements / delivered in several sermons by the late reverend and faithful minister of Christ, Mr. William Bridg ...</title>
                  <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 182 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Crouch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: portrait lacking on film.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Love --  Religious aspects --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57690:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57690:1"/>
            <p>THE FREENESS OF THE GRACE and LOVE OF GOD TO BELIEVERS DISCOVERED.</p>
            <p>In reference to
<list>
                  <item>1. Their Services and Sufferings:</item>
                  <item>2. Their Conſolations, and</item>
                  <item>3. Their Salvation and Eternal Glory.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Together with
<list>
                  <item>The Excellency of the fear of God.</item>
                  <item>The Goodneſs and Pleaſantneſs of Brotherly Love.</item>
                  <item>The Wiſdom of Hearing the Voice of the Rod.</item>
                  <item>Repentance the only way to prevent Judgements.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Delivered in ſeveral Sermons by the late Reverend and faithful Miniſter of Chriſt Mr. <hi>William Bridg,</hi> ſometime Preacher of the Word of God at <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Crouch</hi> in Exchange-Alley over againſt the Royal Exchange in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:57690:2"/>
            <head>The Reader is deſired before he begin, to correct theſe material faults, beſides ſome literal ones, which he is deſired to pardon.</head>
            <p>IN pag. 9. &amp; 10. and in ſeveral places, for <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,</hi> r. <hi>Judicial:</hi> p. 11. l. 10. blot out <hi>the door of:</hi> p. 18. l. 17. for <hi>Judicious,</hi> r. <hi>Judicial:</hi> p. 61. l. 1. for <hi>renewed,</hi> r. <hi>removed:</hi> p. 99. l. 19. r. <hi>humbled for the want of Faith:</hi> p. 114. l. 2. r. <hi>as he increaſeth in Godlineſs:</hi> p. 129. blot out the <hi>firſt line.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:57690:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Labours of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Author (now with God) both in Print and in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, have already prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him in the Gate, and make his name and memory ſtill remain, and continue like a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Oyntment, notwithſtanding the vain endeavours of ſome, to make both himſelf and Writings ridiculous: in which kind, though they may be abundantly repayed, ſince a late Author makes ſome on all ſides guilty of the like; yet there is cauſe to fear, (whatſoever innocent deſign may be pretended by thoſe <hi>Witty men</hi>) that Religion it ſelf may be
<pb facs="tcp:57690:3"/>contemned and ſlighted by ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices.</p>
            <p>It is hoped that theſe Sermons will give no occaſion for ſuch Cavills, but that they may be of uſe to ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to direct, and confirm them in the good old wayes of God, though they may want much of thoſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, which it may be the Authors own hand would have beſtowed upon them. And upon that Account, the Reader is deſired not to be offended, though ſome things may not be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act or plain as might be wiſhed, nor to impute it to the Author in the leaſt, but to look upon it only as the fault of the Tranſcriber, or Publiſher.</p>
            <p>Yet hoping that notwithſtanding theſe diſadvantages, ſome may (through the bleſſing of God) reap profit and benefit by them, they are here publiſhed and ſubmitted to the Judgement of the Candid Reader.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. O.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:57690:3"/>
            <head>Upon the Death of Mr. <hi>William Bridg</hi> a faithful and painful Labourer in the Lords Vineyard.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>EVen as a Lamp that ſpendeth liberally</l>
               <l>It's Oyle, that we may do our work thereby:</l>
               <l>Or as a ſparkling Star, which ſhineth bright,</l>
               <l>Thereby directing Travellers by night:</l>
               <l>Or as the Sun, that by his cheerful rayes</l>
               <l>Diſperſeth darkneſs, and his beams diſplayes,</l>
               <l>On the cold Earth, whereby he makes it ſpring</l>
               <l>With fruitful crops, which joyfulneſs doth bring:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Bridg</hi> diſpers'd his fruitful beams whilſt here,</l>
               <l>But now he's fixed in a higher Sphere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You that have skill, ſorrow and joy to blend;</l>
               <l>Somewhat of both upon this Prophet ſpend.</l>
               <l>Grieve for your loſs, and yet rejoyce in this</l>
               <l>He's gone from trouble to a place of bliſs:</l>
               <l>Mourn, that you did no more improve his pains;</l>
               <l>And yet rejoyce, that he now reaps the gains.</l>
               <l>Weep that ſo bright a Lamp no longer ſhin'd;</l>
               <l>Yet joy in thoſe choice works he left behind.</l>
               <l>Mourn that ſuch Lights do ſet, and when ye'ave done,</l>
               <l>Joy that he's there, where needs not Moon nor Sun;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57690:4"/>
               <l>Which never ſhall be ſtained with a night;</l>
               <l>But hath eternal Glory for its Light:</l>
               <l>And let thoſe darkned intervalls you ſee,</l>
               <l>Increaſe your longing in that place to be:</l>
               <l>For here are changes; Prophets too muſt dye;</l>
               <l>Yet let me that expreſſion molliſie.</l>
               <l>If the Philoſopher of old could ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All of me ſhall not dye;</hi> then ſure we may</l>
               <l>Tranſcendently affirm of <hi>Bridg,</hi> that he</l>
               <l>Yet lives, and ſhall live to Eternity:</l>
               <l>He lives in Heaven, on Earth he doth the ſame:</l>
               <l>There in his Soul, Here in his Works and Name.</l>
               <l>And though his Body now be turn'd to Duſt;</l>
               <l>Yet at the Reſurrection of the juſt,</l>
               <l>Each Atom ſhall be gathered, ſo to raiſe</l>
               <l>A glorious fabrick to his Maſters praiſe;</l>
               <l>And Soul and Body jointly then ſhall ſing,</l>
               <l>Grave where's thy Conqueſt, Death where is thy ſting?</l>
               <l>And then in Triumph ſhall aſcend on high,</l>
               <l>Having obtain'd through Chriſt, the Victory.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57690:4"/>
            <head>SERMON I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. 20.15, 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Is it not lawful for me to do what I will with my own? Is thine eye evil becauſe I am good? — So the laſt ſhall be firſt, and the firſt laſt; for many be Called but few Choſen.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> DO intend (God willing) to ſhew you the freeneſs of the Grace of God in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to mens <hi>Employments</hi> and <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and therefore have made choice of this Scripture, wherein you have the Parable of certain Labourers in the Vineyard, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is propounded and applyed; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded from <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>For the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57690:5"/>Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a man that is an Houſeholder, which went out early in the morning to hire Labourers into his Vineyard, and when he had agreed with the Labourers for a penny a day, he ſent them into his Vineyard; and he went out about the third hour, and ſaw others ſtanding in the Market-place; and he ſaid unto them, go ye alſo into the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and whatſoever is right I will give you, and they went their way; and again he went about the ſixth hour, and the ninth hour, and did likewiſe; and about the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth hour he went out and ſaw others idle, and he ſaid unto them, Why ſtand you here all the day idle? And they ſaid unto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man hath hired us: he ſaid unto them, go you alſo into the Vineyard, and whatſoever is right, that ſhall you receive. So when Even was come, the Lord ſaid unto his Steward of the Vineyard, call the Labourers and give them their hire, beginning from the laſt even to the firſt, and when they came that were hired about the eleventh hour, they received every man a penny, but when the firſt came they ſuppoſed that they ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more, and they likewiſe received eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man a penny, and when they had received it, they murmured againſt the good man of the houſe, ſaying, theſe laſt have wrought but one hour, and thou haſt made them equal to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57690:5"/>us that have born the burthen and heat of the day. But he anſwered one of them, and ſaid, friend I do thee no wrong; didſt thou not agree with me for a penny? take that thine is, and go thy way; I will give unto this laſt, even as unto the firſt: Is it not lawful for me to do what I will with my own? Is thy eye evil, becauſe I am good? ſo the laſt ſhall be firſt, and the firſt laſt; becauſe many are called, but few choſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus far the Parable goes, to ſhew that all is of free Grace, both for ſervice and for ſuffering. Now if you mind the firſt Verſe of the Parable, you will find it brought in with a <hi>for. For the Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a man,</hi> &amp;c. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter ſaith, <hi>For we have forſaken all to follow thee, and what ſhall we have. But Jeſus ſaith, he that hath forſaken Father or Mother, Wife or Children, Houſes or Lands for my ſake, ſhall receive a hundred fold, and inherit eternal life; and they that are laſt ſhall be firſt, and the firſt ſhall be laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſhall it be in <hi>ſuffering,</hi> many that are firſt ſhall be laſt; and ſo it ſhall be in <hi>ſervice,</hi> in <hi>employment</hi> and in <hi>labour.</hi> For after he had ſpoken this Parable of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, he concludes <hi>the laſt ſhall be firſt, and the firſt laſt;</hi> concluding for ſuffering and for ſervice: and he gives the Reaſon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57690:6"/>of it from our Election; <hi>for many are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but few choſen:</hi> and ſhews the grounds of it, that it is of free grace, <hi>the firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt firſt.</hi> So that as to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and as to ſuffering, all is of free grace. Now take theſe words as they are in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the former, and they will afford us this Doctrine:</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That there is much of the freeneſs of the grace of God, laid out both in our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and ſufferings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Free grace in the matter of our ſervices and labour, and free grace in the matter of our ſufferings. <hi>The firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt firſt: for many ſhall be called, but few choſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the proſecution of this Doctrine, I ſhall</p>
            <p>Firſt, Labour to ſhew you, That it is a great mercy to be uſed for God, and by God, either in a way of ſervice or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for his Name.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That there are ſome that God doth eſpecially ſingle out to ſerve him, or to ſuffer for him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That it is the free grace of God, that one ſerves above another.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſhall ſhew wherein this free
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57690:6"/>grace of God doth appear or ſhine forth in the matter of our employment and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I ſhall ſhew, why God will or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and diſpoſe of our ſervices and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in the way of free grace, or free love.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, it is a great mercy to be uſed for God or by God in the matter of ſervice or ſufferings, it is a great mercy to be employed in any work for God. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The more ſerviceable any man or woman is for God, the more they honour God; and the more they honour God, the more will God honour them: when I te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie of any excellency in God, then I honour God: when God teſtifies of any honour in me, then God honours me; as now when God calls me to any ſervice, then God teſtifies an excellency in me, then God honours me: when a Governour puts any honour upon a common Souldier, he calls him forth to ſpecial ſervice: ſo it is an honour for a man to be ſerviceable to God. This was the honour of <hi>Moſes, Moſes the ſervant of the Lord:</hi> and when the Holy Ghoſt puts an honour upon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>The Pſalm of</hi> David <hi>the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord:</hi> Not the Pſalm of <hi>David</hi> the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> no, the Pſalm of <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57690:7"/>the ſervant of the Lord. So in the New Teſtament this was <hi>Pauls</hi> honour, <hi>Paul the ſervant of the Lord.</hi> Now is it not a great honour to honour God, and to be owned by God? Thus it is with them that ſerve the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The more ſerviceable any man is for God in his Generation, the more apt God is to accept of his work, though there be failings in the work: obſerve what great failings there was in <hi>Aaron,</hi> yet God accepted of the work.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The more ſerviceable any man is whileſt he lives, the more comfortably he will dye, when he comes to dye: what is a mans comfort upon his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, but that according to his meaſure he hath ſerved God? ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Glorifie me Oh Father, for I have done the work that thou haſt ſent me to do.</hi> And ſo it is a mans comfort to do the work that God gives him to do; yea, it will be his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort at the day of death.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The more ſerviceable any man is whilſt he lives, the more he ſhall ſpeak when he is dead: there are them that being dead yet ſpeak: why, what ſpeaks <hi>Abell,</hi> but Faith, good Works, good Examples? He offered a better Sacrifice than <hi>Cain,</hi> he was truly ſerviceable to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57690:7"/>God in his day, and now he ſpeaks when he is dead; Thus <hi>Abell</hi> did, and thus it is with a ſerviceable man. Look how it is with a wicked man that is ſerviceable to the Devil, and that writes wicked and wanton Books that ſpeak when he is dead; ſo is it with a man that is ſerviceable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. This honour is in the ſervice of God above all others; and to ſay no more, this is the thing that is deſired more in ſome reſpects, than the enjoyment of Heaven, <hi>I deſire</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all: yet nevertheleſs for your ſakes, and the ſervice of the Churches I deſire to live.</hi> So that I ſay in one reſpect this is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable than Heaven; for no ſuch work is to be done in Heaven. And is it not a great matter, very great to be ſerviceable unto God, to be uſed and employed by God either in ſervice or ſuffering?</p>
            <p>Secondly, As it is a great mercy to ſerve for God, ſo is it not a great mercy to ſuffer for God: to be called out to ſuffer for the Name of Chriſt? For ſaith the former Chapter, <hi>We have forſaken Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, Wife and Children, Houſes and Lands for the ſake of Chriſt; but ſaith Chriſt, he that forſakes ſo much for me, ſhall receive a hundred fold, and eternal life; yea,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57690:8"/>he that ſuffers for me, ſhall reign with me.</hi> You carry a burthen, but Chriſt carries the heavy end, and you have communion with Chriſt alſo thereby; and thereby alſo your heart ſhall be filled with comfort, yea, even the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt: the Spirit of God dwells in every believer; and that man that ſuffers for God, the Spirit of God reſts upon him, as the Dove reſted upon the Earth: and ſo ſaith <hi>Peter, the Spirit of God and of glory reſteth in you.</hi> A man is never more glorified, than when he ſuffers for God: remember that: When our Saviour Chriſt was upon the Croſs, he was then glorious before the eyes of Heaven, and never more glorious than then; for <hi>now is the Son of man glorified:</hi> ſo may you ſay when in ſufferings, Now am I glorified: Oh, the glory of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian! Nay, ſayes the Martyr when going to the Stake, <hi>Now I begin to be a Chriſtian.</hi> And thereby he is aſſured of eternal life and ſalvation. <hi>Our preſent light afflictions</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>works an eternal and exceeding weight of glory.</hi> And ſayes our Saviour, <hi>If ye be reviled and reproached for my ſake, happy are you.</hi> And if you look into <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.28. you will find, that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings are an evidence to us. Thus now you ſee, it is a mercy, yea, a great mercy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57690:8"/>to ſuffer for the Name of Chriſt. That is the firſt thing.</p>
            <p>But then Secondly, There are ſome that God doth graciouſly ſingle out to ſervice, or to ſuffer for him; this honour all the Saints have not, but ſome God doth gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſingle out not only to ſervice, but to ſuffer for him. Now there is a provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential ſervice, and there is a mercenary ſervice; there is a judicious ſervice, and a gracious ſervice; ſome that God doth ſingle out graciouſly: poſſibly a man may be <hi>providentially</hi> uſed in the ſervice of God; thus <hi>Naaman</hi> had a ſervant in his houſe, that was providentially made uſe of for his Converſion. So I ſay, a man may be made uſe of providentially, and alſo mercinarily and judiciouſly: ſo the Devils have been; <hi>Whom ſhall I ſend to be a lying Spirit in the mouth of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? Send me, and he went.</hi> This is a judicious ſervice: and thus the Devils do ſerve for wages; and them alſo that are the Inſtruments of the Devil: Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are judicious ſervers; they are them that make clean the diſhes: ſo that I ſay, there are them that may ſerve God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntially, mercenarily and judiciouſly. Providentially, and ſo all the creatures ſerve him. Mercenarily, ſo they ſerved
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57690:9"/>him that ſaid, <hi>Lord, Lord, have we not done many wondrous works, yet Chriſt ſayes he never knew them, depart from me.</hi> And then there is a Judicious Service, as when God gave licence and power to deſtroy the ten Tribes: but then, as there is a Providential ſervice, a Mercenary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and a Judicial ſervice; ſo there is alſo a <hi>Gracious ſervice;</hi> There are ſome that God doth graciouſly ſingle out to ſerve him, and to ſerve him in ſuffering for him. Did not God graciouſly ſingle out <hi>Caleb</hi> to ſerve him? For it is ſaid, <hi>he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed God fully:</hi> and did not God in the New Teſtament ſingle out <hi>Paul? Go thy way to</hi> Ananias, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. <hi>And he trembling and aſtoniſhed ſaid, Lord, what wilt thou have me to do? And the Lord ſaid, ariſe, go into the City, and it ſhall be told thee what thou ſhalt do.</hi> So I ſay, God doth graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſingle out ſome, not only to ſerve him, but to ſuffer for him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What is it that makes the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, that ſome are employed in the work and ſervice of God, when others are not? It is only the free grace of God. It may be, you may think it is from men, that the providential hand doth fall upon one more than upon another; or that it is the will of men to ſingle out whom they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57690:9"/>will for ſufferings; but it is only the free grace of God. Look what the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty of God doth in a way of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and affliction, that the free grace and love of God doth in a way of mercy. As now, ſuppoſe two men be together in a transgreſſion, one is ſingled out to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the other is not: Why? The Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty orders it ſo: <hi>Think ye that they on whom the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Tower of</hi> Siloam <hi>fell, were greater ſinners than others:</hi> No: a man may be wrapt up in great afflictions and calamities as <hi>Job</hi> was: and why ſo? It is the Soveraignty of God, I will do what I will with my own: ſo look what Gods Soveraignty doth in a way of judgement, the ſame the free grace of God doth in a way of mercy. Oh! Is it not a great mercy to be ſingled out to ſuffer for the name of Chriſt, Phil. 1.29. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you it is given, not only to believe, but to ſuffer for Chriſt.</hi> So I ſay, it is not only to believe, but to ſuffer: and ſo God doth graciouſly chooſe ſome and not others for this great work.</p>
            <p>But Fourthly, Wherein doth the free grace of God ſhine forth and appear in the matter of our ſervices and ſufferings?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, In many things: Will you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with your own employments? What is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57690:10"/>reaſon one man is called forth to an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and not another? It is only the free grace of God. What is the reaſon one man hath ſucceſs in a work, and not another? It is only the free grace of God. But to clear it the more unto you; the more unlikely any perſon is to ſerve or ſuffer for God, the more the free grace of God ſhines forth in that perſon. Now who are thoſe that God doth generally make uſe of in his ſervice, but thoſe that are the moſt unlikelieſt perſons? As now will you inſtance in matter of mens places, Eſtates, Callings; there was two ſervants concerned in the converſion of <hi>Naaman,</hi> the ſervant of the Prophet, and <hi>Naamans</hi> own ſervant: Who is moſt likely now? certainly the ſervant of the Prophet; yet you ſee the other doth it: ſo that I ſay, the unlikelieſt oftentimes God makes uſe of; which is to ſhew forth the freeneſs of his grace: Will you inſtance in the matter of ability as to the Miniſtry, who more unfit and unlikely to be uſed in the Goſpel, than a company of Fiſhermen, poor Fiſhermen? for it is ſaid, they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived they were unlearned, and yet you find them made uſe of by our Saviour for the promulgation of the Goſpel. Will you inſtance in the matter of free grace?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57690:10"/>Who was ſo commended as <hi>Nathaniel</hi> that ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to Chriſt? <hi>Behold an Iſraelite indeed, In whom there is no guile.</hi> Who more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to be uſed in Gods ſervice than <hi>Paul</hi>? Was it likely <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould bring any honour to God, who was whipt and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged up and down Town like a Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor? yet this man preached: and do you think he was like to do any good by his preaching? yet you find it is ſaid, <hi>he did more than they all;</hi> and God bleſſed his Miniſtry, and he converted the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Why is this but to ſhew that God will make uſe of them that are moſt unlikely to do him ſervice: <hi>For they that are firſt ſhall be laſt;</hi> and this only to ſhew the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his grace.</p>
            <p>But wherein doth the grace of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as to our ſufferings? for the great thing is to ſtand our ground: To this I anſwer;</p>
            <p>Firſt, Is it not a great mercy, that the great God of Heaven and Earth ſhould call us worms to bear witneſs to his Name, his great Name, yea, to ſuffer for it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Is it not a great mercy and favour, that God will take notice of all the injuries that are done unto them that ſuffer for him, as done unto himſelf? <hi>I know thy works</hi> (ſaith God) do men jeer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57690:11"/>thee and reproach thee for the ſake of Chriſt? then happy art thou. What wrong is done unto them that ſuffer for God, he takes it as done unto himſelf: So that I ſay, it is a great mercy and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that the God of Heaven ſhould take thoſe injuries as done unto himſelf, that are done unto us. Nay, (ſaith God) <hi>I will give you a mouth, and tell you what you ſhall ſpeak when you come before men. Take no thought for what you ſhall ſpeak, for it ſhall be given you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Is it not a great mercy, that your hearts ſhall be filled with joy in the midſt of ſufferings? <hi>They went away rejoice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Is it not a great mercy, that ſome ſhall ſtand, that are likelieſt to fall, when others fall, that were likely to ſtand?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Is it not a great mercy, that thoſe whom the adverſaries think ſhall diſhonour and marr the work of God, that they ſhould bring more honour to God, and ſuffer more powerfully and ſtrongly for him than others, and that they ſhould be uſed moſt for God?</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Is it not a great mercy, that when God ſeems to have moſt diſpleaſure againſt us, his Love ſhould be then moſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57690:11"/>ſet upon us, as it is in ſufferings? Who would but think, that when we are given into the hands of wicked men, it is from the diſpleaſure of God againſt us, when yet it is from the free grace and great love of God unto us?</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Is it not a great mercy, to conſider, that what is our greateſt miſery <hi>ſeemingly,</hi> that that ſhould contribute to our greateſt mercy? Thus it is in our ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings for the Name of God: You ſee what great and wondrous things were done by the death of Chriſt; and ſo alſo what wonders were done by <hi>Joſeph</hi> in <hi>Aegypt</hi> when he was ſold thither by the maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of his Brethren; It is the way of God unto his people, that the more others work to do them <hi>harm,</hi> the more God doth order it to prove for their <hi>good;</hi> which is only from the free grace, love and favour of God. We never did any work yet, but free grace paid us for it: even the work of ſuffering, God payes us for that: He was a Preacher to day, yet carried to Priſon, that paid him for it. Yea, Chriſtians are paid for the work they never did: and what is the Reaſon of it, but only the free grace of God. Thus you ſee wherein the free grace of God appeares and ſhines forth.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57690:12"/>
            <p>Fifthly, Why will God carry on the work of our ſervices and ſufferings in the way of free grace? Why, God will order our employments and ſufferings in a way of free grace, that we may not be proud of them: We are apt to be proud of our employments and ſufferings, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God will carry on his work ſo, as that he may keep us from the ſin of pride and haughtineſs, when we ſhall conſider it is the free grace of God to ſingle us out to ſervice or ſufferings. Why ſhould we be proud? God loves to confound the wicked and ungodly in the world, by making thoſe that are the moſt unlikely, to be ſerviceable to himſelf; and by orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their ſervices and ſufferings in a way of free grace. This God doth to confound the Wiſdom and Reaſon of worldly men. <hi>Many are called, but few choſen.</hi> God hath ſet the weak to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the ſtrong. Again, God doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of his work in a way of free grace, that none may be diſcouraged from his ſervice, or ſuffering for him. If none but great, and mighty, and holy men were to be uſed in Gods ſervice, then the weak would be diſcouraged and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, and we ſhould be ready to ſay, I am not worthy. Now God doth ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57690:12"/>and diſpoſe of his work, as not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the weak, but to give encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all. Well then if ſo, A word for Application. Is this a Truth that we have heard, that all that God doth either as to the ordering of our ſervices or ſufferings is in a way of free grace? What have we then to ſay, but as Job, <hi>The Lord gives, and the Lord takes away; bleſſed be the Name of the Lord?</hi> You ſay, that God chooſes whom he pleaſes to ſerve him, or to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for him; and that it is out of free grace: if ſo, why ſhould not <hi>all</hi> ſuffer? But you hear it is not all, but ſome, that God doth graciouſly ſingle out to ſuffer for himſelf.</p>
            <p>But here ſome may ſay, <hi>I am weak, and do not any work for God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But give me leave: Is Family work no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? The Apoſtle inſiſts much upon that in his Epiſtles, he calls much upon Parents, Children, Maſters, and all to do their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Reformation work is a great work, or elſe the Apoſtle would never have ſpoken ſo much of it, and exhorted ſo much to it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Is it nothing to do the work of your generation? to do the work that is ſuitable unto your condition? All men are not called to all works: there is a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57690:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>peculiar work to every man. Now is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting work nothing? Is ſupporting work nothing? Is relieving work nothing? This comforting work it is Angelical work. Is it nothing to improve the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent that God hath given thee? This will be the great Queſtion at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Faithful, or not faithful? There are none but have Talents more or leſs, which they muſt then anſwer for.</p>
            <p>But you may be ready to ſay, <hi>I have no work.</hi> That is a miſtake; for there are none but have work: therefore look unto that which is your work.</p>
            <p>But you may ſay again, <hi>Though I have work and ſervice, yet my ſervice may be a judicious ſervice, or a mercinary ſervice, or a providential ſervice: Now how ſhall I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh my ſervice, Whether it be a provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential, a judicious, a mercenary ſervice, or whether God hath graciouſly ſingled me out to ſerve him in a way of free grace and love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to this, take theſe two or three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If it be a work or ſervice given you by free grace, then God will lead you more and more, and bring you to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the deſign of his work. When <hi>Peter</hi> was called to open the door of the Temple, at firſt he did not know
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57690:13"/>the deſign, but afterwards he was told it. So thus it is with thee: If God do call thee to work, he will acquaint thee with the deſign of the work.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you ſerve God in a way of free grace, then you will be contented with your work: yea, you will be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be uſed for God, to be laid out for God, you will ſay, I am contented, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath called me.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, When God doth make uſe of a man in a way of free grace, then that man doth not make any great bargains for himſelf: they that ſerve God any other way, will make great bargains for themſelves, make uſe of his ſervice to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their eſtates: But now they that ſerve God out in a way of free grace, will not do ſo. Therefore now you that are at work, do you pocket up at work? Do you make great bargains for your ſelves? If ſo, this is no free grace work.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, <hi>I am afraid I do not ſerve God in a way of free grace, becauſe I have no ſucceſs in my work. But you may obſerve in the Scripture, that ſometimes a man may be called to work by free grace, and may have ſucceſs at the beginning, as</hi> Joſeph <hi>had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, and yet the ſucceſs may leave him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57690:14"/>
            <p>As now there are them that preach many years, and never convert one ſoul, yet this ſhould not diſcourage them; for free grace may call you to a work, and yet you may not find that ſucceſs in it which you expected.</p>
            <p>But then again, here is the great Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on yet behind; <hi>Suppoſe God doth deal with the children of men in a way of free grace and love, then what is my duty, and what ſhall I do, that I may ſo ſerve and ſuffer, as to ſerve and ſuffer under the conduct of free grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to this, you may take it in theſe following particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, if you would ſerve and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer under the conduct of free grace, then ſerve your call fully; and go to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of the thing called unto, leaving God to do his work: Do your work to the utmoſt, and leave God to do his. When God called <hi>Joſhuah</hi> to do a work fully, and he did it, God ſhewed mercy to him, and to his poſterity after him: And ſo when <hi>John</hi> was called to a work, and he did it by halves, God blew upon him, and upon his poſterity after him. Therefore I ſay, when God calls us to a work, let us do our work fully, and leave God to do his work.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57690:14"/>
            <p>Secondly, If you would ſerve God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of free grace, then when you find any warmth or heat upon your affections, take the hint of this opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the doing of that work God calls you to.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you would ſerve God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of free grace, then do not envy others that are more employed, that have better ſucceſs, and are better paid than your ſelves: obſerve how it is with two Servants in a great Shop, the one at one end, the other at the other end; the one may take more money than the other, yet they do not envy one another: and why? but becauſe they both ſerve one Maſter. Thus it ſhould be with the Saints and ſervants of God, they all ſerve one Maſter; and therefore one ſhould not envy another, becauſe he is more employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or hath better ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If you would ſerve God under the conduct of free grace, then be ſure you do not ſerve for wages: be not mercina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in your ſervice. It becomes thoſe that ſerve under free love to be very free in their ſervice: ſaith one, I have been wrought upon by my Neighbour, and ever ſince I have endeavoured to do him good. Now it is God that hath wrought upon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57690:15"/>us by his free grace; and if ſo, let us free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve him, and labour to do him all the honour we can. When the Prodigal firſt thought of returning home unto his Fathers houſe, he ſaith firſt, <hi>Let my Father make me as one of his hired ſervants.</hi> This was a Legal expreſſion; I will be hired, <hi>Let him make me as one of his hired ſervants;</hi> but when he ſaw his Fathers love, he talked no more of his hired ſervice. Inheritance is not of the Bond-woman, but of the free. I do confeſs indeed, it is not unlawful to look unto the recompence of reward: yea, it is lawful for us to do it. But now do you deſire to ſerve under the conduct of free grace, then look not for wages; do not do as an hireling, as the labourers of the Vineyard: no, do it freely in a way of love, thankfulneſs and believing.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If you would ſerve under the conduct of divine love, then ſerve God with fear upon the account of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Work out your ſalvation with fear and trembling, for it is God that worketh in you both to will and to do of his good pleaſure.</hi> If you do ſerve and work, then fear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Gods goodneſs to you.</p>
            <p>And to conclude this Application: If you would ſerve as thoſe that ſerve under
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57690:15"/>the conduct of free grace and love; then have a care that in all your workings you depend upon nothing but the free grace of God in reference to your call: and if ſo, why then ſhould you not willingly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the Name of Chriſt? would you know whether you are <hi>called</hi> to ſuffer? why, this is a certain Rule, when the caſe is ſo with you, that you muſt either ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer or ſin.</p>
            <p>But then a ſecond word of Application may be this. Is it ſo, that ſo much of the free grace is laid out in reference to our ſervices and ſufferings? Then Firſt, Let us freely and willingly ſuffer for the Name and Cauſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Is it ſo, that ſo much of the free grace of God is laid out in reference to our ſervices and ſufferings? then why ſhould we not be contented with our ſufferings; not only contented in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or contented upon ſuffering, but contented with ſufferings: Our Saviour tells us, that <hi>they that will be his Diſciples muſt deny themſelves, take up the Croſs and follow him:</hi> Not only take up the Croſs, but follow him; yea, and deny themſelves. Some will deny themſelves in this or that, but will not take up the Croſs: but ſaith our Saviour, <hi>If any man will follow me, let
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57690:16"/>him take up the Croſs and follow me.</hi> Thus now, if Chriſt calls us to ſuffer, let us ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer freely, becauſe his grace is free.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you would ſerve under the conduct of free grace, then take heed of any Legal <hi>therefore</hi> upon your ſufferings, Matth. 9.27. <hi>Then anſwered</hi> Peter, <hi>and ſaid unto him, behold, we have forſaken all and followed thee, what ſhall we have therefore?</hi> This was a Legal <hi>therefore;</hi> Chriſt anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſaid, <hi>You ſhall have your reward, but many that are firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt firſt.</hi> The only way to take away this Legal <hi>therefore,</hi> is to look more and more upon the free grace of God either in your ſervices or ſufferings for him; for thus all muſt do, that either ſerve God or ſuffer for him, under the conduct of free grace: Do you deſire to ſerve God ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as to employments or ſufferings un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of free grace and love? then look more and more upon his free grace, and depend upon it in reference to your call, in reference to your aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, in reference to your dependance, and in reference to your reward, ſeeing all is of free grace, bleſs the name of the Lord. Thus it is both in ſuffering work, and in ſervice, <hi>the firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57690:16"/>
            <p>Therefore as you would deſire to ſerve or ſuffer under the conduct of free grace, rejoyce and bleſs God for his free grace; remember this, that whether we ſerve or ſuffer, it is of free grace.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how the free grace of God ſhines forth both in our ſervices and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; <hi>Is it not Lawful for me to do what I will with my own, is thine eye evil becauſe I am good, ſo the laſt ſhall be firſt and the firſt laſt, becauſe many are called but few choſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57690:17"/>
            <head>SERMON. II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 THES. 2.16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father which hath loved us, and given us Everlaſting Conſolation and good hope through Grace; Comfort your hearts and eſtabliſh you in every good word and work.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HAving already treated of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the grace of God in reference to our Imployments and ſufferings; I do intend to ſhew you alſo the freeneſs of the grace of God, in reference to our Comforts and Conſolations; and this Text you ſee ſaith, <hi>God hath given us Everlaſting Conſolation,</hi> and tells us ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that <hi>God hath given us this everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conſolation through grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore without any further expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, you ſee that free Love is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57690:17"/>upon all our ſpiritual Comforts. For what is more free than gift? <hi>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father hath given us everlaſting Conſolation and hope through grace;</hi> Therefore it is by the grace, by the free grace of God, that we are truly comforted:</p>
            <p>There is much of the freeneſs of Gods grace and love laid out in our ſpiritual comforts and conſolations.</p>
            <p>For the opening of this Argument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſhew you that it is a great mercy to be truly Comforted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is poſſible for Gods own people, to live a great while without any conſiderable Comfort.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is not in the power of any Creature, or any thing on this ſide God or Chriſt, to comfort a poor diſtreſſed drooping ſoul.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That when God doth give or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow comfort upon any, he gives and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes it in a way of free grace.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To ſhew wherein the grace and love of God is manifeſted, in the matter of our ſpiritual Comforts.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Why God will deal with us in the way of free grace and love, in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our comforts.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When a man may be truly ſaid to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57690:18"/>be comforted in a way of free grace and love.</p>
            <p n="8">8. What a poor drooping ſoul muſt do, that he may be truly comforted in a way of free love; and in caſe he be ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, what returns he ſhould make. Of theſe in order.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay it is a great mercy to be truly comforted: For it is a promiſed mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and promiſed mercies are no ſmall mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; now this is a mercy promiſed, Mat. 5.4. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, As this is a mercy promiſed, ſo it is the proper birth, fruit, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the holy Ghoſt, Gal. 5.22. <hi>But the fruit of the ſpirit is love, joy, peace, long ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith.</hi> Joy and peace are the proper fruits of the holy Ghoſt, and therefore no ſmall mercies.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As this comfort is the proper birth, fruit, and effect of the holy Ghoſt; ſo it is the main part of the Kingdom of God, Rom. 14.17. <hi>For the Kingdom of God is not meat nor drink, but righteouſneſs peace and joy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> It is a main part of the Kingdom of God, and if ſo, no ſmall matter.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This comfort is reward alſo,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57690:18"/>as well as a main part of the Kingdom of God. Comfort and Joy in the holy Ghoſt is both duty and reward; ſo it is promiſed in the forementioned Scripture, Matt. 5. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted;</hi> and if ſo then ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is no ſmall thing.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, As it is duty and reward, ſo it is that grace whereby you are inabled to read your other graces. When a man is under great Temptations, Sorrows, and Afflictions, it is a hard thing to read his graces; but now this helps us to read our Graces: ſome will ſay they cannot read their graces, they lie at the bottom; As to explain it, take this plain compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, There are many Fiſhes in a Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pond, but now in rainy and foul wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fiſh lye all at the bottom, and are not to be ſeen; but in fair weather the fiſh ſwim and are viſible: So if it be foul weather upon a ſoul, if it be dark and gloomy weather, the ſoul cannot read his graces; but now when God ſhines upon him, then he is inabled to read them, yea though his graces lye at the bottom as I may ſay, yet the poor ſoul is abl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o read them, and if it be ſo, it is no ſmall thing, 'tis no ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to read our graces, our other graces.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57690:19"/>
            <p>Sixthly, As it is that grace whereby you are inabled to read your other graces, ſo it is that whereby you joy in all good things. Grief and ſorrow ſtreighten the ſoul, ſtreighten the heart, but joy and comfort dilate the ſoul, widen and open the heart. Pſalm 119.32. <hi>I will run the way of thy Commandments, when thou ſhalt enlarge my heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, As by this grace you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to joy in all good things, ſo it is alſo that grace, whereby you are inabled to bear up againſt every evil thing; to bear up under all afflictions: Are you reproached? by this comfort you are inabled to bear up againſt reproaches; for ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, If you be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached for the name of Chriſt, happy are you:</hi> Are you reproached? Comfort will turn that to your benefit and bleſſing: Are you perſecuted? <hi>Bleſſed are you when men ſhall revile and perſecute you, rejoyce,</hi> &amp;c. Are you not only perſecuted but beaten too? Comfort will bear up your hearts under all ſtripes, and afflictions; for we find <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> ſung in the Stocks: well but this is not all.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, This is that grace that will ſtrengthen and eſtabliſh you in the good waies of God. Mark how they go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57690:19"/>in 2 Theſſ. 2.16, 17. <hi>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father which hath loved us, and hath given us everlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace, comfort your hearts, and ſtabliſh you in every good word and work.</hi> Comfort and eſtabliſhment go together, and if it be ſo, it is no ſmall matter.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, This is that grace that will give a beauty and luſtre to your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. The comforted Chriſtian is the truly beautiful Chriſtian. If a man have never ſo much beauty in his face, yet if his face be wrinkled with grief, and blubbered with tears, the beauty of his face is not ſeen; but when joy and comfort comes, that wipes off all, and his beauty then is ſeen. So here, comfort doth not only take away reproach from your profeſſion, but it gives a luſtre, a beauty to your profeſſion; the comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtian I ſay is the truly beautiful Chriſtian; and if ſo, ſurely it is a great mercy to be truly comforted.</p>
            <p>That is the firſt thing in general, that it is a great mercy to be truly comforted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As it is a great mercy to be truly comforted, ſo it is poſſible for Gods own ſervants and deareſt children, to live a long time without any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57690:20"/>comfort, any fundamental comfort, their hearts may faint; <hi>My heart and my ſoul fainteth</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt: and you know how it was with <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 10.17. You may ſee how he was bowed down, he complains <hi>there was no ſtrength remained in him, till there came one and touched him, and ſet him upon his legs again:</hi> a good man may faint and want comfort, and all the former comforts that he hath had may be Eclipſed. <hi>Reſtore to me the joy of thy ſalvation,</hi> Pſalm 51.12. ſaith <hi>David;</hi> his glory and comfort was eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: yea poſſibly a gracious ſoul may live a long time without comfort; <hi>How long wilt thou forget, yea forget me O Lord, what for ever?</hi> Pſalm 13.1. I ſay a man may live a long time without any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable comfort. There is a time when God will try his people; and ſee whether they will take comfort from his hand, or from another hand; it may be it may be ſo with you ſometimes: God may try, whether you will wait upon him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, and reſt upon him for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As a man may live long without comfort, ſo it is not in the power of any thing, on this ſide God and Chriſt, to give comfort to a poor drooping ſoul:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57690:20"/>this is the Lords prerogative. <hi>I am the Lord that comforteth.</hi> This is his name. <hi>Father of mercies, and God of all comfort and conſolation;</hi> and 2 Cor. 7.6. <hi>Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs God that Comforteth thoſe that are caſt down comforted us,</hi> &amp;c. It is Gods prerogative only, to do it, comforting work is creation work; it is not in the power of the creature, but of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Iſa. 57.19. <hi>I create the fruit of the lips, peace, peace to him that is afar off, and to him that is near ſaith the Lord, and I will heal him.</hi> It is Gods work to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and not in the power of any other; Man may be inſtrumental to comfort, but it is none but God alone that can do the work.</p>
            <p>But ſome may object and ſay, can none but God alone comfort?</p>
            <p>No none but God alone can rate off Satan. If a great dog, or maſtiff be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying a child or a ſheep, a ſtranger comes and ſtrikes him, and calls him off, but the dog takes no notice of him; but when the Maſter comes, he rates him off preſently; none but the Maſter can do it. So here it is none but God that can rate off Satan from worrying the poor droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul, when it is under temptation, none but God the Maſter: It is not in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57690:21"/>the power of any creature, but in the power of God alone; it is in the power of none but the third perſon in the Trinity, the ſpirit of God: what needed the third perſon in the Trinity to have come into the world as he is now, if any other could comfort. As none can redeem but Chriſt the ſecond perſon of the Trinity; becauſe the ſecond perſon came from Heaven on purpoſe to redeem. So none can comfort but God, and his ſpirit; becauſe the third perſon came from Heaven to do it, there is none but God alone that can comfort a poor ſoul.</p>
            <p>That is the third particular.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When God doth beſtow comfort, he beſtows it, and gives it in a way of free grace, in a way of free love, and grace. See but how they go together in the Text, <hi>Who hath given us everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſolation through grace.</hi> I will give you one Scripture more to prove it, and conſider it well, <hi>Job.</hi> 33. you have there the draught of a mans Converſion. <hi>Firſt,</hi> he goes on in his ſin; and all on a ſudden God gives in a word to him at 14, 15, verſes. <hi>For God ſpeaketh once, yea twice, but man perceiveth it not: In a dream, in a viſion of the night, when deep ſleep falleth upon men, in ſlumberings upon
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57690:21"/>the bed, Then He openeth the ears of men, and ſealeth their inſtruction,</hi> and then the ſoul is filled with horror of conſcience, as in verſe 19. <hi>He is chaſtned alſo with pain upon his bed, and the multitude of his bones with ſtrong pain.</hi> And when God hath done thus, then he juſtifies him, and gives him faith, and ſhews him true righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, as in verſe 23. <hi>If there be a meſſenger with him, an interpreter one among a thouſand, to ſhew unto man his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs;</hi> This is juſtification, and when this is done, then the Lord comforts him, as in verſe 25. <hi>His fleſh ſhall be freſher than a childs, he ſhall return to the days of his youth.</hi> You ſee God comforts him in a way of free love; and in the 26. verſe <hi>He ſhall pray unto God and he will be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable unto him, and he ſhall ſee his face with joy, for he will render unto man his righteouſneſs.</hi> God comforts in a way of free love, he comforts how he pleaſeth, and as far as he pleaſeth; but whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he comforts, it is ſtill I ſay in a way of free love. You may ſee it in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65.14. It is ſaid, <hi>Behold my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but you ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall howl for vexation of ſpirit; and thus alſo ſaith the Lord</hi> in the former verſe; <hi>Behold my ſervants
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57690:22"/>ſhall eat, but ye ſhall be hungry, behold my ſervants ſhall drink, but ye ſhall be thirſty; behold my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but ye ſhall be aſhamed.</hi> God comforts whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and as far as he pleaſeth, and it is all free, out of free love; John 14.20. <hi>At that day you ſhall know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you:</hi> and at verſe 16. <hi>And I will pray the Father, and he will give you another comforter, that he may abide with you for ever.</hi> This work of comforting is properly the work of the Holy Ghoſt; and the Holy Ghoſt breathes as the wind, where it liſteth; and therefore I ſay comforts whom and how he pleaſeth, and all in a way of free love and free grace. That is the fourth particular.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Wherein is the love, the free love of God manifeſted to us in the matter of our comforts? I anſwer in many things.</p>
            <p>I will pitch but upon three only.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The greater he is that giveth, and the greater the thing is that is given, and the leſſer or meaner the perſon is, that the thing is given unto, the more free is the love of him that gives and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows the thing. Now this comfort and conſolation is a great thing, it is a very great matter, it is a birth of the Holy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57690:22"/>Ghoſt: Is that a ſmall thing? It is part of the Kingdom of God: Is that a ſmall matter? It is both duty and reward: Is that ſmall? It is that which exceeds all the Joy of the world: <hi>Lift up the light of thy countenance upon me: Thou haſt put more gladneſs into my heart, more than in the time that their oyle and their wine Increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> Pſalm 4.7. Ask a poor drooping ſoul, and he will tell you that it is a great thing, for it comes from a great God. Iſaiah 57.15. <hi>For thus ſaith the high and lofty One, that inhabiteth eternity, whoſe name is holy; I will dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite Ones;</hi> Unto that ſoul that trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, unto that ſoul will God bring com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and will be nigh unto him. Now if a Prince ſhould riſe from his Throne, to come and help up a poor fallen Crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; would it not be looked upon as an act of very great favour: Yet thus God does, when he comes to comfort, the great <hi>high and lofty One,</hi> comes down from his Throne, as it were to lift up a poor drooping ſoul: O what free grace is this! But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The more God doth croſs hands,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57690:23"/>(underſtand me) the more I ſay that God doth croſs hands in the matter of our comforts, the more doth the free grace of God appear in our comforts; when <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſſed <hi>Joſephs</hi> two children, <hi>he croſt his hands, and he laid his right hand upon the younger, and his left hand upon the elder; not ſo father ſays</hi> Joſeph; now what doth this ſhew but only the freeneſs of his love; and ſo if God ſhall croſs hands in the matter of our comfort, what doth this argue but the freeneſs of his love, and grace; and God doth ſometimes do thus when he comes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, he doth croſs hands. Sometimes two men have been in the ſame tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the one hath been comforted, and the other not: what ſhall we ſay of <hi>Peter,</hi> and of <hi>Francis Spira. Spira</hi> having profeſſed the Truth, and being called to witneſs to it, did deny it; ſo did <hi>Peter,</hi> he denied Chriſt, yet <hi>Peter</hi> was comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but <hi>Spira</hi> never comforted, but lay deſpairing and roaring out to his death, <hi>I am a reprobate, I am a reprobate, no hope for me, no hope for me; Peter</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, <hi>Spira</hi> was never comforted: What do you think of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Cain, Cain</hi> murders his brother <hi>Abel</hi> a godly man; <hi>David</hi> murdered <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> a godly man too:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57690:23"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> had been with him in all his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and was a very good man, but though <hi>David</hi> was an adulterer alſo, yet a meſſenger is ſent to him that ſays, <hi>thy ſins are forgiven thee:</hi> but <hi>Cain</hi> not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, but driven out from the preſence of the Lord. So that I ſay there may be two in a tranſgreſſion, and the one may be comforted, and the other not. Look into the Scriptures, and into your own experiences, and you will find great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners comforted, and leſſer ſinners not comforted, and great ſinners converted and comforted ſooner than others. <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> was a great ſinner, and yet was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted: the <hi>Jaylor</hi> was a great ſinner, and yet comforted; and yet many that have walked very cloſely with God, have not been comforted. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 88.15. <hi>Hemau</hi> complains ſadly in verſe 14. <hi>Lord why caſteſt thou off my ſoul, why hideſt thou thy face from me: I am afflicted and ready to dye from my youth up: while I ſuffer thy terrors I am diſtracted;</hi> and yet he walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cloſe with God, as you may find in the former part of the Pſalm. Yet we find ſometimes (I ſay) the greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners converted and ſooneſt comforted. Now what is this but croſſing of hands in the matter of our comforts, and this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57690:24"/>is only to ſhew forth the freeneſs of the grace of God; and the free grace and love of God is moſt abundantly, moſt eminently manifeſted to the ſoul by this croſſing of hands.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The more unbelieving any man is that is comforted, the more doth the freeneſs of the grace of God appear. Dearly beloved Brethren, it is with our conſolation, as it is with our juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and our ſanctification; when God comes to juſtifie a man he finds him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, yet <hi>He juſtifies the ungodly,</hi> and not only the ungodly, but the unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alſo; and therefore the Lord ſaid, <hi>Go and compel them to come in;</hi> They were unbelieving perſons, yet God calls them: And ſo it is alſo in the matter of our ſanctification; when God comes to ſanctify men, He finds them unwilling to be ſanctified; but as God juſtifies them though unwilling, becauſe he doth it freely; ſo He ſanct fies them too though unwilling, becauſe he ſanctifies freely: And ſo it is alſo in the matter of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; when God comes to comfort, he finds the ſoul unwilling many times, <hi>my ſoul refuſed to be comforted</hi> ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt <hi>Pſalm</hi> 77.2. and ſo again, <hi>Remember the word unto thy ſervant, upon which thou
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57690:24"/>haſt cauſed me to hope,</hi> Pſalm 119.49. I was unwilling, but thou cauſedſt me to hope whether I would or no. When God comes to comfort, He doth it though men are unwilling to be comforted: It is very ſtrange that it ſhould be ſo, and yet ſuch is the unbelief of mens hearts, that as before converſion they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be turned, ſo after converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they are unwilling to be comforted. Now this is that I ſay, that the more unwilling any man is to be comforted, yet if God doth comfort him, the more free doth the grace of God appear in it; God doth comfort though ſouls are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing: O the freeneſs, the freeneſs of the grace of God, in the matter of our comforts. Thus you ſee how and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the free grace of God appears, and is manifeſted in our ſpiritual comforts and conſolations. That is the fifth parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Why will God deal with us in a way of free grace, in the matter of our comforts and conſolations? would it not be better in a way of ſettlement, in a conſtant way; would not that be beſt? No, take notice of this, that there is no way to make a mercy ſure like this; I know no mercy that is ſo ſure, as that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57690:25"/>which is wrought and given in a way of free grace, and free love, they go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Text; <hi>Everlaſting Conſolation through Grace:</hi> The only way I ſay to make a thing ſure, is to receive it in this way, in which God gives it, that is, in a way of free grace. Pray tell me, did not God chuſe <hi>David</hi> freely, and his houſe? Yea, it was freely in oppoſition to the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.21. Says <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Michal Sauls</hi> daughter, <hi>It was before the Lord, which choſe me before thy Father, and before all his houſe; to appoint me ruler over the people of the Lord, over</hi> Iſrael, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God choſe him freely, alſo in oppoſition to his own brethren: And was not his houſe ſure; the covenant was ſure: 2 Sam. 23.5. <hi>Although my houſe be not ſo with God, yet he hath made with me an everlaſting covenant, ordered in all things and ſure, for this is all my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and all my deſire.</hi> God hath made me his choſen, and his mercies to me are ſure; God will deal with us in a way of free grace, that our mercies may be ſure; <hi>By grace ye are ſaved,</hi> and if ſo, what a comfort is it that God will ſo order and diſpoſe of it that we may be ſure of it, and depend upon it; for God will have us depend upon him for our ſpiritual
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:57690:25"/>comforts, and what will make us more depend upon him, than to know that he gives all in a way of free grace; we muſt depend upon God both for our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and our outward comforts, ſeeing what He doth He doth freely; we muſt freely depend upon him for comfort. But,</p>
            <p n="7">7. When may a man be ſaid to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comforted in a way of free grace? I cannot deny but I am comforted (ſaith a poor ſoul) but I know not whether it be in a way of free grace and free love; now how may I know that I am comforted in a way of free grace.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak to this <hi>Negatively</hi> and <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>Negatively,</hi> There is a comfort that is the daughter of time; a man or woman is ſorrowful, but time wears it out, time comforts him; this comfort that ſprings from, and ariſeth out of time, is not true comfort; neither is that man truly comforted by free grace. But when the ſoul is truly comforted in a way of free grace, then he is comforted by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing witneſs that he is the Child of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a comfort that ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from the ſatisfaction of a natural
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57690:26"/>conſcience: A man knows by nature, that there is a God, and that this God is to be prayed unto, and therefore he prayes accordingly; and when he hath done, his natural conſcience is ſatisfied, and he is then comforted; but no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if a mans comfort ariſe only from this, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m the ſatisfaction of a naturall conſcience, that man is not truly comforted; for he that is truly comforted, is comforted by joy in believing: <hi>in whom believing ye rejoyce,</hi> Rom. 15.13.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is a comfort that ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from a mans non-attendance to his own condition. Men may be comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Why? Becauſe they never look into their condition, how it ſtands between God and their ſouls: There is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ariſing not only from a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but from the non-attendance to his own condition, and hereupon he is ſecure: but this is not the comfort that ariſeth from free grace and free love.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, There is a comfort that doth ariſe from the uſe of the creature, men are troubled in their minds, and they run preſently to the Tavern, to their Muſick, or merry Company to put it off; and ſo it may be are comforted: but if a mans comfort ariſe only from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57690:26"/>he is not truly comforted, not comforted with the comfort of free grace and love: he that is comforted in this way, it is but a diverſion to him, and not true comfort: as ſtraw when ſet on fire will make a flaſh and a flame, but black aſhes remain behind; ſo when men are troubled, and they run to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, or to Muſick, and merry Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; all this is but a flaſh, black Aſhes remain behind: provoked trouble will be angry trouble, and angry will be moſt troubleſome; when men run to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment to divert trouble, they provoke it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, There is a comfort that doth ariſe from the common work of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; <hi>Some who have taſted of the Heavenly gift, and are made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and yet fall away, Heb.</hi> 6.4. The falſe ground <hi>received the word with joy:</hi> Now if a mans comfort ariſeth from theſe common workings of the Holy Ghoſt, it is not true comfort: for he that is truly comforted, is comforted in a way of free love, his comfort is unſpeakable, 1 Pet. 1.8. <hi>Whom having not ſeen you love, in whom though you now ſee him not, yet believing ye rejoyce with joy unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and full of glory.</hi> Thus you ſee <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57690:27"/>when a man is not truly comforted in theſe five particulars; a man is not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comforted from time, nor from the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of a natural conſcience, nor from a non-attendance to his condition, nor from the uſe of the creature, nor laſtly from the common workings of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But Secondly <hi>Affirmatively,</hi> we have heard when a man may be ſaid not to be comforted. Now when may a man be ſaid to be comforted, truly comforted in a way of free grace? Beloved in the Lord, are you willing to have your comforts tried; falſe and counterfeit things do not love trial; now if you be willing to be tried, to have your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts tried, it is a ſign and a hope that your comforts may be true; but I ſhall not inſiſt on this. There are two or three things I ſhall ſpeak to here.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you have been comforted by the word of promiſe, ſet on upon your ſouls by God, then are you truly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in away of love and free grace, for what is the promiſe but the word of grace. But ſome may ſay, I have had a promiſe, but I fear it may be from the Devil; for the Devil may bring a promiſe: did he not bring a pomiſe unto Chriſt, Mat. 4.6. <hi>Saying, He ſhall give His Angels charge over
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57690:27"/>thee, and in their hands they ſhall bear thee up.</hi> This promiſe was brought to Chriſt by the Devil, and it may be my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe may be handed to me by Satan, and ſet on upon my ſoul by him. But do but mark this, I will only ſay this one thing to thee, poor ſoul, to eaſe thee of this objection. If Satan bring a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to you, it is to lead you into ſin, to draw you into ſin, and to that which is evil, as this to Chriſt here, <hi>He will give His Angels charge concerning Thee, caſt thy ſelf down.</hi> He brought a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to do evil, caſt thy ſelf down: but now if God hand a promiſe to you, it is for your doing of good; therefore ſays Chriſt to Satan, <hi>It is written</hi> I have a word and a promiſe too, <hi>It is written thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God:</hi> The Devil brought this that he might do evil, and God gave Chriſt a word to keep him from evil: and ſo when you are brought into temptations, great temptations; if you have a word of promiſe brought home to your hearts, to bear you up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der temptation; it is not the Devil that gives it in to you, that hands it to you: No, for the Devil is no friend to faith, no friend to ſtay you up; for the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter will not act againſt the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57690:28"/>ſaith <hi>Luther, though the Devil be Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, yet he is not Omnipotent; though he be Mighty, he is not Almighty:</hi> And therefore I ſay, if you have a promiſe comes to you, to help you to do good, it is not of Satan but of God; for he is Almighty, he is able to comfort. That is the firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Would you know whether you be comforted in a way of free grace and love, you may know it by the eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and flowing of your comforts, which will ebb and flow according to the cauſe: They ſay the <hi>Marygold</hi> opens and ſhuts with the Sun, when the Sun ſhines it opens, when the Sun with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws it ſhuts, it opens and ſhuts ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the withdrawing and ſhining of the Sun: and ſo if your comforts be true, the more the righteouſneſs of Chriſt opens before you, the more the Sun of righteouſneſs ſhines upon you, the more you will be comforted: If your comforts be true, the more the freeneſs of the love of God is opened to you, the more will the comfort of the ſoul be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged; if your comforts be true, the more God ſhines with his countenance, the more is the ſoul comforted: Lord ſaies <hi>David</hi> in Pſalm 4.6. <hi>Lift up the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57690:28"/>light of thy countenance upon us, Thou haſt put more gladneſs in my heart than in the time that their Corn and their wine increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> Now according to the opening and ſhutting of theſe things, ſo will your comforts be. How is it therefore with you? Is there any ebbing and flowing? How is the righteouſneſs of Chriſt? How is the light of Gods countenance diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to you? Are they laid open to you? Then are you truly comforted in a way of free grace and love. That is the ſecond.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you be comforted in a way of free grace and love, then your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are true friends to holineſs of life. That comfort that is wrought by the grace of God without you, is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt friend to the grace of God within you, and to holineſs in your lives: Falſe comfort is a friend to ſin, a neighbour; a guard to ſin; but no friend to true and gracious comfort; yea thoſe that have this falſe comfort can indure ſins againſt conſcience: But now where there is true comfort, and comfort from the grace of God, there conſcience is as the Apple of the Eye, and the man cannot indure the leaſt ſin, he cannot bear the leaſt Mote of ſin to lie upon his conſcience: How
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57690:29"/>is it therefore with you? is your comfort a friend to holineſs of life? and can you ſay, the more comforted I am the more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am? Then you are truly comforted.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe I want comfort now, and that I am one of a drooping, trembling ſpirit, and of an afflicted heart; what ſhall I do that I may be comforted, and comforted in a way of free grace? I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer;</p>
            <p>Firſt, Go away, and be ſenſible of your unbelief; for it is want of believing that hinders our comfort, and when the comforter comes, he will convince the world of ſin, and eſpecially of unbelief: would you then be comforted in a way of free love? Go then I ſay, and be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of your unbelief, and be humbled for it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Obſerve what thoſe things are that hinder your ſpiritual comforts, and take heed of them. They are many. I will only name ſome of them. As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Worldly fears, and worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights; theſe are enemies to true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Sins againſt conſcience, they that ſin againſt knowledge, will hardly have peace of conſcience; nay it is pitty they ſhould have peace, leſt they be
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57690:29"/>ingaged and incouraged thereby to ſin; thoſe that ſin againſt Conſcience will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have peace. Do you think to have the Spirit to be your friend whom you grieve ſo often, if then you would be truly comforted, you muſt have a great care of ſinning againſt conſcience, and thereby grieving the ſpirit, that <hi>ſpirit whereby you are ſealed to the day of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi> Epheſ. 4.30. would you then be truly comforted? Obſerve I ſay theſe things that hinder your ſpiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: can you think that what you grieve moſt, ſhould comfort you moſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as you expect true comfort, have a care of grieving the ſpirit of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If at any time God make a tender of grace, or offer a word of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and peace to you; be ſure you do not refuſe it. We are apt to refuſe to be comforted; but be ſure you accept of it, eſpecially in a time of Temptation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Be ſure you do not reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your own performances in reference to your comforts. Brethren and Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved think on theſe things, and compare them with your own daily experiences. I ſay if you would be truly comforted, do not reſt on your own performances. As we are apt to reſt upon our own
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57690:30"/>Righteouſneſs, in reference to our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; ſo we are apt alſo to reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our own performances, in reference to our comforts. O take heed you do not go about to eſtabliſh your own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts upon the bottom of your own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, for if you do, you will not ſubmit to the conſolations of God.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If you would be comforted in a way of free grace and love, then ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy much the freeneſs of the grace of God. What is the reaſon people are no more comforted? It is becauſe they ſee no more of the grace of God, the free grace of God: the more you look into the riches and freeneſs of Gods grace, the more you will be comforted.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If you want comfort at any time, walk graciouſly in the want of it. When you want comfort go to God and ſay; <hi>Lord although I cannot ſee thee, yet will I ſerve thee; and although I cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy thee, yet I will obey thee; and although I cannot ſee thy face, yet I will follow after thee, if by any means I may obtain thee.</hi> Walk graciouſly in the want of your comforts.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Set your ſelf to rejoyce in him that gives you comfort, <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord alwaies, and again I ſay rejoyce,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57690:30"/>ſaith the Apoſtle,</hi> Phil. 4.4. He doth not only ſay humble your ſelf for ſin, which is a duty and a great duty; but he ſaith <hi>Rejoyce, and again I ſay rejoyce in the Lord;</hi> Rejoyce in the Lord who gives you comfort freely. As much as you have been humbled for ſin formerly, ſo much ſhould you now rejoyce that you have been comforted, and freely comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the grace of God; Rejoyce ſo much in the Lord of your comforts.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, (To name them only:) If you would be comforted in a way of free grace and love, then be thankfull for your comfort: He that is thankfull for a little, ſhall have much; be thankfull therefore to God for your comfort.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Would you be comforted in a way of free grace and love; then go to God for that comfort: Friends and Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; God is willing, moſt willing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; and what will you not go to him? God is willing to make good his name, and his Title; now this is one of his Titles, I am the Lord that comforteth: He is willing to do what Chriſt was ſent to do; <hi>the ſpirit of the Lord is upon me to comfort all that mourn,</hi> Iſa. 61.2. Is not God willing to do it; He hath ſent the comforter alſo to comfort you, yea he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57690:31"/>hath given his Miniſters charge to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you; <hi>Comfort ye, comfort ye my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> Iſa. 40.1. and are not you willing now, to receive what God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſs, I will come unto you.</hi> John 14.15. You will be troubled and reaſon with your ſelves, yet I will not leave you comfortleſs. <hi>As one whom his mother comforteth, ſo will I comfort you, and ye ſhall be comforted.</hi> Iſa. 66.13. Therefore now O poor drooping ſoul go to God, for he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to comfort thee, if thou be but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to go unto him. Only in your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God obſerve theſe two or three directions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, When you go to God for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, go to the Office which he hath ſet up for comfort, the Office of the Holy-Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When you go to God, ſhut your eyes, and caſt your ſelf at an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon the free grace of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In going to God for comfort you muſt ſtay Gods leaſure; ſome come and ask of God, and becauſe they do not receive an anſwer preſently, they are gone; but be ſure you do willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtay Gods leaſure. Thus I ſay, would you have comfort? you muſt obſerve
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57690:31"/>theſe things, to go to Gods Office, to ſhut your eyes, and to caſt your ſelves at adventure upon the free grace of God, and then you muſt ſtay Gods leaſure; Thus doing you ſhall be truly comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and when you have obtained this comfort, and are thus truly comforted; Then take theſe few rules with you, and ſo I conclude.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Take as much pains to keep your comfort, as ever you did to get it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Labour more and more to increaſe it, for if it do not increate, it will certainly decreaſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Be comfortable to, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting of others; for how do you know but that God hath comforted you, to this very end that you might comfort others; <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo, and be ſure to ſhew comfort, for comforts ſake.</p>
            <p>Brethren and Beloved in the Lord, Do not receive this grace in vain; But go all you that have this comfort, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the riches of Gods grace, the freeneſs of the grace of God that hath comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, and ſay, <hi>What ſuch a one as I comforted! Others of thy Children Lord have walked cloſely with Thee, but I have walked looſely; and ſhall I be comforted and not they? O what free grace is this! I have
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57690:32"/>been a great ſinner Lord, and what am I comforted? O what free grace is this! There are ſome that have walked in the light, and they are now in darkneſs; but I have walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the dark, and yet am now in the light, O what free grace is this!</hi> Go away therefore, and magnifie the riches of Gods grace in the matter of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</p>
            <p>Thus you have heard how the freeneſs of the grace of God is written upon all your comforts, your comforts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations are all deeply inamelled with the free grace of God; and that much of his free love is laid out in your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and conſolations. And thus I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the words of my Text, <hi>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father, which hath loved us, and given us Everlaſting Conſolation and good hope through grace; Comfort your hearts and eſtabliſh you in every good word and work.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:57690:32"/>
            <head>SERMON. III.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPHES. 2.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For by grace are ye ſaved through faith, and that not of your ſelves; it is the gift of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the former exerciſe I have been ſhewing you the freeneſs of the love and grace of God, in the matter of our comforts and divine conſolations. I ſhall now in the third place ſhew you the freeneſs of the grace of God, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to our ſalvation, and eternal glory, and therefore follow theſe words which the Apoſtle ſpeaks at the latter end of verſe 5. <hi>By grace are ye ſaved,</hi> and ſo you ſee the ſame in verſe 8. <hi>For by grace are ye ſaved and that not of your ſelves; it is the gift of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why ſhould he ſay the ſame words again in ſo ſhort a compaſs? Why, it
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:57690:33"/>was to ſhew, not only that his heart was full of the free grace and love of God, but to ſhew alſo that he thought he could never ſpeak enough of it, and therefore he repeats it, <hi>by grace ye are ſaved; For by grace are ye ſaved:</hi> that is to ſay from firſt to laſt, you are ſaved by the free grace and love of God.</p>
            <p>From whence then I take up this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That there is much of the free love and grace of God laid out in the matter of our ſalvation and eternal glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the clearing of this point, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew you,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it is a matter of infinite happineſs, and of great concernment to go to Heaven and to be ſaved for ever.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To ſhew you how this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is obtained, this mercy of ſalvation and eternal glory; I ſhall ſhew, it is of free grace and free love.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall anſwer two Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſhall ſhew you wherein the free grace and love of God appears in the matter of our ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Shew you why God chuſeth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:57690:33"/>to ſave the children of men in a way of free love and grace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſpeak a little by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction: It is a great matter, and of infinite concernment to be ſaved, and to go to Heaven forever. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, You are thereby ſaved from wrath to come; you count it here a great matter to be delivered from the wrath of man; but it is a far greater mercy to be delivered from the wrath of Devils, to be delivered from their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and malice, and not to lye at their mercy to all Eternity. Yea,</p>
            <p>Secondly, You ſhall be delivered from all ſorrow, both inward and outward, and if ſo, how bleſſed, and happy are you, for you ſhall die in the Lord; <hi>And bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the dead that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev</hi> 14.13. It is a mercy to have meat and drink, and a bed to lye on, but it is a greater mercy not to need them; in Heaven you ſhall be freed from theſe needs and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. You walk here, but it is with a burden; you hear now, but it is with a burden; you repent now, but it is with a burden: But in Heaven you ſhall be freed, not only from the guilt of the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of duty, but from the burden of duty
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57690:34"/>alſo, Heaven knows of no duty that hath a burden with it. Thus you ſhall be freed. Again,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, You ſhall not only be freed from theſe troubles, but you ſhall alſo be brought into a poſſeſſion, <hi>into an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance that is incorruptible, that fadeth not away;</hi> where you ſhall enjoy the company of Saints and Angels, and that without ſuſpicion, or jealouſie one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: here you have the company of Saints, but either you ſuſpect them or they you, either they are jealous of you or you of them; but Heaven knows no ſuſpicions, no jealouſies; Saints live there without ſuſpicions.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If you go to Heaven and be ſaved, you ſhall then be filled with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: if you have but a little taſte of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry here you are ready to break under it, under a little glory; but the time will come, when you ſhall be filled with glory, and your hearts ſhall bear up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, your bodies ſhall be changed; <hi>your vile bodies ſhall be changed, and made like unto Chriſts glorious body;</hi> you ſhall be filled with glory, ſoul and body both. Yea,</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If you be ſaved, your graces ſhall be alwaies in Act, alwaies in exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe; your underſtandings ſhall be fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57690:34"/>your difficulties ſhall be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and you ſhall ſee them all little and eaſie unto you, and your wills, hearts and affections ſhall be drawn out to God, with infinite ſatisfaction and infinite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; <hi>I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs,</hi> Pſalm 17.15. All de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light ariſeth from enjoying things ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, now what is more ſuitable for a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional creature, than to enjoy his ends: when a Husband hath been at ſea from his wife half a year, or a year; what joy is it to her to ſee him come home again. So for a poor ſoul to ſee Chriſt, what joy is it after he hath withdrawn himſelf a great while? here we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt but in part and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted; but then you ſhall be ever, for ever with the Lord, and have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him without interruption. Now we ſee joy and glory, but darkly; and if there be ſo much ſweetneſs to ſee Chriſt in a glaſs; O then what ſweetneſs will it be to ſee him face to face, and enjoy him for ever; And to ſay no more,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If you be ſaved, you ſhall have the knowledge of the continuance of this condition: Though a mans condition be never ſo happy in it ſelf, yet if he think it will not continue,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:57690:35"/>that man is unhappy in the midſt of his happineſs; this is the unhappineſs of Hell, men ſhall know and be aſſured that they ſhall never be delivered out of it, never, never, never; and this is the happineſs of Heaven, that men ſhall alwayes rejoyce, and ſhall be aſſured that they ſhall ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to do, ever, ever, ever.</p>
            <p>But 2. In what way does a man come to this attainment, how and in what way is a man ſaved? Why in a way of free love and grace, for if God beſtow any thing in a way of gift it is free, for what is more free than gift; now do but conſider what thoſe things are, which are called in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, Salvation, and you may obſerve, that they all come in a way of gift.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sometimes Salvation is put for the Author of Salvation, Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace, according to thy word, for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation:</hi> Luke 2.29, 30. That is Chriſt the Author of our ſalvation; and ſo ſaith Chriſt to <hi>Zacheus, This day is ſalvation come to thy houſe;</hi> That is Chriſt. Now this ſalvation is obtained in a way of gift, <hi>Saith Chriſt to the woman of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, if thou hadſt known the gift of God, and who it is that ſaith unto thee give me to drink,</hi> &amp;c. John. 4.10. He calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57690:35"/>the gift of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Sometimes Salvation is put for the means of ſalvation, for the Goſpel; <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation.</hi> Heb. 2.3. that is the means of ſalvation, the goſpel: this ſalvation is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo called the gift of God; <hi>unto you it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Mat. 13.11.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Sometimes ſalvation is put for eternal glory, <hi>who would have all men to be ſaved, Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> and this ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is the gift of God too. Rom. 6.23. <hi>But the gift of God is eternal life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> Now ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as to the Author of it, as to the means of it, and as to the ſalvation it ſelf, it is all of free grace, all given in a way of free love and grace; and therefore it muſt needs be, that much of the free grace and love of God is laid out in our ſalvation.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, if it be ſo, that by free grace we are ſaved, then what need we uſe the means of ſalvation; you ſay we are ſaved by grace, by free grace; wherefore then need we indeavour.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Yes we are to indeavour; do you not uſe your indeavour to get your daily bread? and yet that is the gift of God:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:57690:36"/>your livelihood is the gift of God; for you ſay, <hi>give us this day our daily bread;</hi> it is then the gift of God, and yet we are to uſe the means: and ſo we are to do what we can, although not what we ſhould in the matter of our ſalvation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by our endeavour, and uſing the means we ſhew our dependance upon God, and our obedience to him, becauſe he hath commanded it; For,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Although I ſay with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>by grace ye are ſaved, and not of works:</hi> yet works are neceſſary, good works are neceſſary in regard of our thankfulneſs to God; and neceſſary as they are an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our ſalvation, ſaith the Apoſtle, although I ſay by grace ye are ſaved, yet you are to be in the performance of good works; Eph. 2.10. <hi>For we are his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works;</hi> the ſame word, <hi>good works:</hi> that is the third general. But.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Wherein doth the freeneſs of the grace of God appear, in the matter of our ſalvation?</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is a great deal of free grace in this, that God ſhould ordain us to eternal life and ſalvation. 2 Tim. 1.9. <hi>Who hath ſaved us, and called us with an holy calling, not according to our works,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57690:36"/>but according to his own purpoſe and grace, which was given us in Chriſt Jeſus, before the world began.</hi> Again</p>
            <p>Secondly, (To name them) Is it not great grace, mercy, and favour that God ſhould ſend his own Son from Heaven to dye for us, and to purchaſe our ſalvation, yet ſo he did. <hi>Ye are bought with a price,</hi> what price? <hi>the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, who gave himſelf a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for you,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.6.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Is it not a great mercy, a very great favour, that we that had broken the firſt Covenant, and had not performed the conditions of it, that we ſhould be ſet up again as I may ſay; That God ſhould ſet us up again, under another Covenant, that runs without any condition; and yet ſo he did, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. <hi>For this is the Covenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael, after thoſe days ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law into their mind and write them in their heart, and I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Yet further It is in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our ſalvation, as it is in the matter of our conſolation, and comfort; and as I ſaid of that ſo I ſay alſo of this. That the greater, and the more glorious any
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57690:37"/>mercy is, &amp; the more worthy and great the perſon is that giveth it, and the more unworthy the perſon is that receives it, the more doth the grace of him appear who giveth it; now what greater mercy, what more glorious mercy, than Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and ſalvation. It is called <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> it is called, <hi>the Kingdom of glory, and Eternal glory,</hi> it is called Joy, <hi>Enter into the Joy of our Lord: and great is the Joy of our Lord;</hi> That Joy which was ſet before Chriſt, that is the Joy of the Saints in Heaven, <hi>It is ſuch as eye hath not ſeen, ear hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. Paul was wrapt up to Heaven, but when he came down he was not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the glory thereof; Thoſe that are in a war are better able to declare the paſſages of it than thoſe that write it, but yet they are not able to declare all. So the Apoſtle could ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this great and infinite glory, but was not able to declare it all. There was one, who was asked by his Prince, <hi>what God was,</hi> he deſired firſt, two dayes to anſwer, when they were paſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57690:37"/>he required four dayes, and after four dayes, he asked eight dayes to anſwer; So if you ſhould ask me what glory that is, which is in my Text, I muſt take two dayes, and then four dayes, and then eight dayes to anſwer, and yet then I ſhould not be able to declare, nor be able to expreſs, this glory which is wrapt up in this one word <hi>Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be this bleſſed Eſtate is beſtowed only upon thoſe that are worthy? No not ſo, this is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly beſtowed upon thoſe that are moſt unworthy: what is more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy than a Dog? why, was not Stephen looked upon as a Dog? yea were not the Gentiles looked upon as Dogs? ſaith Chriſt; <hi>Why caſt ye the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens bread to Dogs?</hi> Now though Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation was of the Jews, for Chriſt came of the Jews, yet Salvation is now for the Gentiles; and among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; who was more unworthy than a blaſphemer, and a perſecutor of the Saints and Servants of God, and ſuch a one was Paul, and yet he was ſaved, though he was not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerving of it, but deſerving the quite contrary; now who more undeſerving than thoſe that deſerve the contrary?
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57690:38"/>yet by grace even they are ſaved, therefore ſaith the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 8.3. <hi>When I conſider thy Heavens, the work of thy ſingers, the Moon and the Stars which thou haſt ordained; what is man, that thou art mindful of him, and the Son of Man that thou viſiteſt him,</hi> &amp;c. So I ſay, that the more glorious any mercy is, and the more unworthy the receiver is, and the greater he is that gives, the more free is the thing given, and thus it is with our Salvation. Salvation is a great, and glorious mercy, and this Salvation is given, and that is great and glorious too, and it is given unto man who is moſt unworthy, and 'tis given by God who is moſt infinite and excellent above us. But again</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The more God doth croſs hands in the matter of our Salvation, the more free is his grace, in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of it upon us: for as I ſhewed you before, that God doth croſs hands in the matter of our comforts, ſo I ſay now, that God doth croſs hands in the matter of our Salvation alſo; For he doth often ſave them that are moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to be ſaved, as <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew the Publican,</hi> and who more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely than <hi>Zacheus</hi> or the <hi>Thiefe</hi> on the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57690:38"/>croſs, or the <hi>Jaylor?</hi> yet were theſe ſaved, though very unlikely to be ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And ſo on the contrary, who more likely to be ſaved, than the young man in the Goſpel, that came to Chriſt, yet you know he was rejected: the young man he comes unto Chriſt, and ſays, Matt. 19.16. <hi>Good Maſter what good thing ſhall I do, that I may have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, ſays</hi> Chriſt, <hi>keep the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, all theſe things have I kept, ſaith he, from my youth upward; then ſaith Chriſt, Go ſell all that thou haſt, and then thou ſhall have treaſures in heaven, and it is ſaid he went away ſorrowful.</hi> Mark now, was not this a forward young man, a very forward man, <hi>all theſe ſaith he have I kept from my youth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> and Chriſt doth not contradict him, and yet notwithſtanding, this man could not do what Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him, he could not ſell all he had, it was too hard for him to learn that leſſon which Chriſt ſet him, for it is ſaid he went away ſorrowful; and and therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>a rich man ſhall hardly enter into the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> And what is this but only to ſhew, that God doth often croſs hands in the matter of our Salvation,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:57690:39"/>to ſhew that <hi>the firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt firſt,</hi> for God loves to croſs hands in the matter of our Salvation; and therefore we find in Scripture, that there are ſome that come to Chriſt and ſay as the Scribe in Matt. 8.19. <hi>Maſter I will follow thee whereſoever thou goeſt,</hi> and Chriſt ſeems to put him off, and yet in the next verſe almoſt he puts one forward, and he excuſes himſelf, and ſayes, <hi>ſuffer me to bury my Father,</hi> but Chriſt ſaith <hi>follow me</hi> &amp;c. Thus you ſee what croſſing of hands there is in matter of our Salvation, to ſhew <hi>the firſt ſhall be laſt I ſay, and the laſt firſt:</hi> Friends, ſtay but a little while, until the day of Judgement, and then you will ſee what croſſing of hands there will be, then you ſhall ſee ſome men at the right hand of Chriſt, whom you thought would never have been ſaved, and then alſo you ſhall ſee ſome on the left hand of Chriſt, whom you would have thought would never have been there. God I ſay will croſs hands in the matter of our Salvation, and the more he doth ſo, the more doth the freeneſs of his grace appear to them that are ſaved. Again</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Yet one thing more, The
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57690:39"/>more our Salvation is layd upon the Arch or Pillar of grace and love, the more free is the grace of God, and the more free it doth appear in the beſtowing of it: Now what are the Arches and Pillars of free grace and love, upon which our Salvation under Chriſt is layd. I ſhall name ſome.
<list>
                  <item>1. The abſoluteneſs of the Covenant.</item>
                  <item>2. That God juſtifies the ungodly.</item>
                  <item>3. That our righteouſneſs is not in us but in Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>4. That the guilt of our ſins by which we lay lyable to condemnation is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</item>
                  <item>5. That a little ſincerity covers a great deal of Infirmity.</item>
                  <item>6. That what God calls ours is not indeed ours, but Gods, as our graces, our duties, which are not indeed ours but Gods.</item>
                  <item>7. That God will in due time gloriſy us and honour us.</item>
               </list> Sin doth provoke God, and cauſeth him to be angry with us, but grace doth provoke him to love us, and therefore the Pillars of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation are layd under Chriſt upon grace, upon free-grace and love, and thereby the freeneſs of the grace of God doth the more appear in the matter of our
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:57690:40"/>Salvation, and that is the fourth General. But then</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Salvation is a work of grace; and ſeeing we are ſaved by grace alone, why then doth God chuſe to ſave men in this way of free-grace? I Anſwer,</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is becauſe this is the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable way unto God; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are not aſhamed to ſay that it is moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to a man to be ſaved by his works, but I am ſure it is more honour, and more honourable unto God to ſave by his free-grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If there was ſomewhat of the good pleaſure of God in the worlds condemnation, all the reaſon in the world then that there ſhould be free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace in the way of Salvation. Pray how came Adam to ſtand for the whole world? He was not choſen by us, why it was the good pleaſure of God that he ſhould ſtand for the whole world, and that he ſinning, we ſhould all be guilty of ſin by, and through him: So I ſay, if there was (as I may ſpeak with reverence) ſomewhat of the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God in the old worlds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, why then ſhould there not be free-grace in the ſouls Salvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15. <hi>But not as the offence, ſo alſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57690:40"/>is the free-gift, for if through the offence of one many be dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift of grace which is by one man, Jeſus Chriſt, hath abounded unto many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God would have Heaven and Salvation to be of one peice, he would have the work of heaven to be all the ſame; Now there were many Angels that fell, and many thouſands that ſtood, why how came they to ſtand, that did ſtand, more than the others that fell; it was only by free grace, they were Elect Angels. Now men and Angels in heaven are of the ſame Quire, and ſing the ſame ſong; and therefore thoſe men that are fated, O who are they? why they are the Elect, and they have great cauſe to glorifie the grace, the free grace of God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God ſaves men in a way of free love, and grace, becauſe none ſhall miſs of Salvation: As God will puniſh, and condemn all the proud, all the wicked, that none ſhall eſcape; So he will alſo ſave all that he hath a mind to ſave, by free grace, becauſe they ſhall not miſs of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, God will ſave men in ſuch a way as whereby he may be glorified to all Eternity, and therefore he ſaves them in a way of free grace and love; For what
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57690:41"/>have we to praiſe God for, in heaven, but only for <hi>free grace, free grace,</hi> to glorify his name for that; therefore I ſay God will ſave men in this way of free love and grace, that he may be thereby glorified hereafter to all Eternity, and thus I have done with the Doctrine; Now go along with me a little by way of application.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If we be ſaved by free grace, if free grace and love be the foundation of our Salvation, why ſhould we not then ſtand cleer from all our own works, as to the meritorious ends of them: for grace and works are oppoſed, and therefore faith as a work can neither Juſtify nor ſave. I confeſs the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>work out your own Salvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, but what follows, for it is God that worketh in you both to will and to do of his good pleaſure, Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If we be ſaved by grace, why ſhould we not be tender of the grace of God, of the name of God, of the free grace of God, and of the great name of God; Are you ſaved by grace, and will you turn grace into wantonneſs? Oh my friends I ſay, if you be ſaved by grace, and by grace alone, how tender ſhould you be of the name of God and of the free grace of God.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:57690:41"/>
            <p>Thirdly, If we be ſaved by grace, then we may here ſee the reaſon, why many do take ſo much pains, as they think, for heaven, and yet fall ſhort of it, and go to Hell; why it is becauſe Salvation lies under the conduct of free grace: Some men abſtain from ſin, that they may not be damned, others perform holy duties, read and hear, &amp;c. That they may go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yea <hi>many ſtrive and ſhall not enter,</hi> becauſe ſalvation is of free grace.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If by grace ye are ſaved, and that there is much of the free grace of God in our ſalvation, why then ſhould you doubt of it: I confeſs it is a hard thing to have Aſſurance of your ſalvation, and if you have it, it is free grace to you more than to another, and free grace is the founder of it if you have it: But yet, O ſoul, if by grace we are ſaved, let us not then doubt of it, for it is moſt ſure: if you are ſaved by grace I ſay, why doubt ye then O ye of little faith. O Chriſtians comfort your ſelves with theſe words, <hi>It is your Fathers good pleaſure to give you the Kingdom,</hi> Luke 12.32. It is his good will and pleaſure, it is in a way of free grace and love.</p>
            <p>But you may ſay though it be in a way of free grace and love, yet it may not be
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:57690:42"/>for me, it may none of it be mine, ſaith the ſoul.</p>
            <p>Nay ſay not ſo, but mark what an Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the Pſalmiſt makes, and draws up from this General. Pſalm 130.4, 5. <hi>But there is forgiveneſs with thee, that thou mayſt be feared. I wait for the Lord, my ſoul doth wait, and in his word do I hope:</hi> and ſo in Pſal. 103. Speaking at large of the grace, mercy and goodneſs of God, in the 8. verſe he ſaith. <hi>The Lord is merciful and gracious, ſlow to anger, and plenteous in mercy:</hi> but what is the concluſion, <hi>Bleſs the Lord all ye his hoſts, bleſs the Lord all his works, Bleſs the Lord O my ſoul.</hi> The very laſt words are, <hi>bleſs the Lord O my Soul:</hi> from the conſideration of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the grace of God in general, he draws up this Concluſion, bleſs the Lord O my Soul.</p>
            <p>But you may ſay: Though God will ſave by grace, yet ſurely all ſhall not be ſaved by grace; ſhall all men be ſaved? is God ſo free?</p>
            <p>No, all men ſhall not be ſaved, <hi>for</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle Gal. 5.15. <hi>We through the ſpirit wait for the hope of righteouſneſs by faith; for in Jeſus Chriſt, neither circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion availeth any thing nor uncircumciſion, but the new creature:</hi> but ſhall not all be
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:57690:42"/>ſaved? No ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, Eph. 5.6. <hi>Let no man deceive you, for no whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger, nor unclean perſon, &amp;c. hath any inheritance in the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of God.</hi> There is no place for unclean things in Heaven: you know what the Apoſtle ſaith to the <hi>Galathians, The inheritance is not to the bondwoman nor to her children.</hi> So that I ſay, that God doth not ſave all, but thoſe he doth ſave, are ſaved by free grace.</p>
            <p>But you would know who thoſe are that are ſaved, or that ſhall be ſaved for ever; why, thus briefly, only to name things,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Look who thoſe are that are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, they ſhall be certainly ſaved.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thoſe that are willing to part with all for Chriſt, and for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Chriſt; they ſhall certainly be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Mat. 19.29. <hi>And every one that hath forſaken houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my name ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold, and ſhall inherit everlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, They that ſtand at Chriſts right hand here, they ſhall be ſure to ſtand at Chriſts right hand, at the day of judgement; and ſo be ſaved. 2 Cor. 5.5.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57690:43"/>
               <hi>Now he that hath wrought us for the ſelf ſame thing is God, who alſo hath given unto us the earneſt of his ſpirit; he that hath wrought us for the ſelf ſame thing:</hi> it is the very ſame word which is uſed for <hi>work out your own ſalvation,</hi> &amp;c. So that there is a working up of the ſoul unto eternal glory; and if Chriſt hath wrought you unto the ſelf ſame thing, whilſt you live here, then you are at his right hand now; and then you may be ſure to ſtand at his right hand, at the day of judgement, and ſo ſhall be ſure to be ſaved for ever to all eternity.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Thoſe that are tender to Chriſts little ones, that are tender to thoſe that are deſpiſed in this world, and ready to help and aſſiſt them according to their wants, they ſhall ſurely be ſaved for ever: <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom prepared for you. For I was an hungred, and ye gave me meat; I was thirſty, and ye gave me drink; I was a ſtranger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ye took me in; I was naked, and ye cloathed me; ſick, and ye viſited me; in priſon, and ye came unto me. And the righteous anſwer, Lord when did we ſee thee ſick, or naked, or hungry, and fed thee, and cloathed thee:</hi> why ſaith he, <hi>In as much as you did it to one of the leaſt of theſe my
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57690:43"/>brethren, ye have done it unto me,</hi> Mat. 25.35. So I ſay, look who theſe are, that are tender of Chriſts little ones, and are ready to help them, and to relieve them according to their wants and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities; thoſe are they that ſhall be ſaved to all eternity.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Thoſe that <hi>ſtrive together for the Faith in times of affliction,</hi> thoſe are they that ſhall be ſaved for ever. Phil. 1.27. <hi>That ye ſtand faſt in one ſpirit, with one mind, ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel.</hi> So I ſay, look who thoſe are, that in the time of perſecution, ſtrive for the faith, they ſhall ſurely be ſaved, and that to all eternity. Yet one thing more.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Thoſe that come to Chriſt in time of Temptation, they ſhall be ſaved free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all eternity: for ſaith our Saviour Chriſt: John 6.39. <hi>And this is my Fathers will that hath ſent me, that of all which he hath given me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhould raiſe it up again at the laſt day;</hi> in verſe 37. ſaies Chriſt, <hi>him that cometh to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out,</hi> and I will give you the reaſon ſaith he, <hi>For it is the will of my Father that I ſhould loſe none which he hath given unto me, but that they ſhould riſe at the laſt day.</hi> How is it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:57690:44"/>with you, (Holy and beloved bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Lord)? Do you come to Chriſt in your Temptations? Do you ſtrive together in love for the faith, in time of perſecution? Are you tempted? Are you brought low? Remember this, that Chriſt is able to raiſe you up, and to ſave you to all eternity; and therefore O ſoul doubt not of your ſalvation.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, I am guilty of this doubting, what ſhall I do that I may not doubt of my ſalvation?</p>
            <p>This is too large a ſubject to ſpeak to now, I ſhall only ſay this to it. Let me deſire you to ſtudy much, the freeneſs of the grace of God in general; and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alſo much, and frequently, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular inſtances of grace and mercy, that God hath ſhewn to others, and you will find it is all of free grace; yea and this ſcripture ſhews you that all is of free grace; and therefore though it be a hard thing for us to get aſſurance of our ſalvation, yet the particular inſtances, and examples of the mercies that God hath beſtowed upon others, ſhould much incourage us, and bear us up, and ſhould ſtir us up to get aſſurance. Grace and mercy being ſhewn to others doth not only ſhew that it may be had,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57690:44"/>but that mercy hath been had. When you ſee the Ice trodden, then you ſay you will venture: So ſay, ſuch a one was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, ſuch a one prophane, and yet he hath obtained mercy, and why may not I? Therefore if you would have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of your ſalvation, think much of the freeneſs of the grace of God; and withal conſider the particular inſtances, and examples of others, that have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this mercy, and that in a way of free grace and love too.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, And laſtly to conclude, Is it ſo, that God ſaves the ſoul freely, and that our ſalvation is only by the free grace and love of God? Why then ſhould we not come with boldneſs for ſalvation, ſince it is ſo free; O let none be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, but let it ſtir us up to come with boldneſs, and to plead for it, if it be free; Is ſalvation free, and will not poor ſinners come to receive it? Come, O come freely for ſalvation, Chriſt Jeſus is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make good his own name, and this is his name, he is called <hi>Jeſus, and he ſhall ſave his people.</hi> This is the will alſo of my Father, that you ſhould come unto me, <hi>John</hi> 6. Chriſt Jeſus hath now ſalvation in his hands, and will you not come and ask for it? But methinks I ſee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57690:45"/>ſalvation in your faces; methinks I hear a voice among you, ſaying, <hi>What ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to which thus: <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus,</hi> and venture your ſalvation upon him.</p>
            <p>And then if you will be ſaved, you muſt become as little children; for ſaith our Saviour, <hi>unleſs you become as little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, you cannot be ſaved.</hi> Mat. 18.3. <hi>You cannot enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> As little children, how? Why, not ſeeking great things; Little children do not ſeek great things, you muſt become as little children, low and humble, not ſeeking great things, for great things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not little children; You muſt be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with all at Chriſts command, and for his ſervice; and for want of this the young man went away without eternal life: <hi>Go and ſell all that thou halt, and follow me, and he could not do it;</hi> and he loſt Heaven by it; he would keep Earth, and he loſt Heaven by it. But once more,</p>
            <p>Be not only willing to part with all for Chriſts ſake, and at his command; but go and caſt your ſelf at adventure upon his free grace and love, and then go and work, and perform duties, and pray, and uſe indeavour; work as if there were no
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57690:45"/>grace to be ſaved by, and bear thy ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſtill upon free grace; work as if the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were no grace, and build upon the grace of God, as though there were no works. Thus do, and you ſhall be freely ſaved to all Eternity, for ever, and for ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:57690:46"/>
            <head>SERMON IV.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>NEHEM. 5.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The latter clauſe of the Verſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſo did not I, becauſe of the fear of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Chapter, there are three things moſt conſiderable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The voice or cry, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Chapter; <hi>And there was a great cry of the people and of their wives, againſt their Brethren the Jews.</hi> And then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, You have made known to you, what <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did in this caſe, in the 6, and 7, verſes, <hi>And I was very angry when I heard their cry, and theſe words, then I conſulted with my ſelf, and I rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the Nobles, and the Rulers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, You hear more of <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> acting at the 14, and 15 verſes, <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57690:46"/>from that time that I was appointed to be their Governour in the Land of</hi> Judah, <hi>from the twentieth year even unto the two and thirtieth year of</hi> Artaxerxes <hi>the King, I and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the Governour: For the former Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours that had been before me, were charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto the people, and had taken of them bread and wine, beſide forty ſhekels of ſilver, yea even their ſervants bare rule over the people: But ſo did not I, becauſe I feared God, becauſe of the fear of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence then obſerve this Truth or Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That thoſe that truly fear God will not do as others do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The true fear of God will keep men from doing thoſe things that other men will do; yea, though an action be to a mans advantage, yet they that fear God will not do it, if it be evil; and ſo it was with <hi>Nehemiah. But ſo did not I, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the fear of God.</hi> For the opening of this we ſhall,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Inquire what it is to fear God; and we ſhall,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Shew you that a man that truly fears God, will do as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:57690:47"/>neither can he do as others do.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We ſhall ſhew you, what there is in this fear of God, that doth lay ſuch a ballance upon mens hearts, that they cannot do as others do.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We ſhall anſwer this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether a man that fears God, may not ſometimes do as others do.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I ſhall ſhew you the Iſſue and Conſequence of this Truth.</p>
            <p>And then I ſhall make ſome Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you ask what this fear of God is, I anſwer in the general. <hi>That it is a paſſion of the ſoul whereby a man doth flee from eminent evil.</hi> But now further, if you ask me what the fear of God is. I ſay that it is twofold.</p>
            <p>A ſervile fear, And</p>
            <p>A ſilial fear.</p>
            <p>A ſervile fear, whereby a man fears God upon the account of Hell, or Judgement, or becauſe of the wrath of God.</p>
            <p>But now a fear of God, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his Judgements, but becauſe of diſpleaſing of him, becauſe of his love, becauſe we would not offend; This is a ſilial fear, to fear him becauſe we would not do contrary to his commands; and thus did <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he would have
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57690:47"/>offered up his ſon <hi>Iſaac: For ſaith God,</hi> Gen. 22.12. <hi>By this I know thou feareſt God,</hi> becauſe he obeyed his command, and was afraid to do contrary.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This fear of God, this filial fear, is not only becauſe of his love, but of his love in conjunction with his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alſo: The greater a man is, the more we fear him, and the nearer he is in relation to us, the more we reverence him. Yet further, as the love of God in conjunction with his greatneſs, calls for our fear; So alſo.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The word and works of God call for our fear; For the word of the Lord is mighty, and his works are won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful; For it is ſaid of God, <hi>That he is fearful in praiſes, working wonders.</hi> Thus if you ask me what this filial fear is, I ſay it is a fear whereby we fear him, becauſe of his love, becauſe of his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and becauſe of his word and works. That is the firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A man that truly fears God, cannot do as others can do; for in the Text we find that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> had an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity in his hand, to <hi>make</hi> himſelf, to <hi>raiſe</hi> himſelf, to make himſelf rich, as to outward things: But you ſee what he ſaith, <hi>But ſo did not I,</hi> as others did, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57690:48"/>I feared God; where the true fear of God is planted in a mans heart, he cannot, he will not do, as other men can and will do: I ſhall cleer this to you by inſtancing in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He that fears God, cannot do as others do in the matter of his choice; you know how it was with the Damſel, the daughter of <hi>Herodias, Mat.</hi> 14.7, 8. when ſhe had danced before <hi>Herod,</hi> He was ſo delighted with her, that he gave her this priviledge, to chooſe what ſhe would, to the half of his Kingdom, and ſhe asked the Head of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt. She was bad, and her choice was bad; not having the fear of God in her heart. But when <hi>Fſther</hi> had her choice, ſhe choſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for ſhe choſe the freedom of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, in the freedom of the <hi>Jews:</hi> ſhe acted not as the other did, becauſe of the fear of God; They that fear the Lord cannot do as others do. I may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo, he would not do as others; for ſaith he, <hi>I will chooſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer Afflictions with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon,</hi> Heb. 11.25. And why did he thus? but only becauſe of the fear of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As they that fear God, will not do as others do in the matter of their
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:57690:48"/>choice; ſo neither will they do as others do in the matter of worſhip: for what ſaith <hi>Joſhua, As for me and my houſhold, we will ſerve the Lord;</hi> Joſh. 24.15. <hi>Do you what you pleaſe. Therefore fear the Lord, and ſerve him in ſincerity and truth, and put away the Gods which your Father ſerved, or the gods of</hi> Amorites, <hi>in whoſe land ye dwell; but as for me and my houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi> As for me I will worſhip God, worſhip you whom you will; thus you ſee what they will do that fear the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Will you inſtance in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of your callings, for a man really is what he is in his calling, in his trade; or will you inſtance in the divine calling, you know what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; Some ſaith he, <hi>Preach Chriſt out of envy, and ſome out of good will,</hi> ſome to get a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood by it, to make a trade of it, to get riches, and honours, and eſtates; but ſo did not I, becauſe of the fear of God; no great advantages will make a man that fears God, to do as others do; he ſaith alwaies, others do ſo and ſo, but ſo will not I, becauſe I fear the Lord.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, A man that fears God cannot do as others can do, in the matter wherein he is intruſted. You know how it was
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57690:49"/>with the Spyes, <hi>Caleb</hi> brought a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> becauſe he feared God; but ſo did not the others.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, They that fear the Lord can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do as others do, in the matter of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. A man that fears the Lord, can love God in adverſitie, and fear him in proſperity. It is ſaid of King <hi>Ahaz,</hi> that he ſinned more and more, becauſe of his afflictions: but <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> did not ſo, when he was under great afflictions, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, for he ſought to the Lord, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured after faith, and ſtrength from him, that ſo he might be eſtabliſhed: but ſo doth not the wicked man, becauſe he feareth not God.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, As there is a great difference between a good man, and a wicked man, or between one that fears the Lord, and one that doth not in the matter of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: So there is a difference alſo in the matter of their refreſhment, in their eating, and drinking, and recreation. Job. 1.5. <hi>And it was ſo, when the dayes of their feaſting were gone about, that</hi> Job <hi>ſent and ſanctified them. Job</hi> ſanctified them, and ſo cannot a wicked man do; but a man that fears the Lord can do this. And,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, A man that truly fears the Lord,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:57690:49"/>cannot do as others do, in the matter of right and propriety: they that fear not God, will take advantage upon others, in the matter of their right and proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. You may ſee what <hi>Abraham</hi> did; <hi>Lot</hi> would not let <hi>Abraham</hi> have his right, though it was his right; yet <hi>Abraham</hi> becauſe he feared God, and for peace ſake, gives up his right; but thoſe that fear not the Lord cannot do ſo. Thus you ſee, that thoſe that truly fear God cannot, will not do as others do, in the matter of his choice, of his worſhip, of his calling, of his afflictions, of his refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or of his right and propriety. And that is the ſecond general. But.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What is there in this fear of God, that ſhould ballance the ſoul, and cauſe it not to do as others do? Why,</p>
            <p>Firſt, By the fear of God a man is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to depart from evil, as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſaith, There are two ſeeds in the world, the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the ſerpent: now theſe two ſeeds rule in the whole world; in ſome the ſeed of the woman rules, and in ſome the ſeed of the ſerpent: now they that are of the ſeed of the woman can fear the Lord, but they that are of the ſeed of the ſerpent cannot fear the Lord; and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:57690:50"/>therefore no wonder that they that fear the Lord cannot, will not do as others do; why, it is becauſe they are of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeed, they are of the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As they that fear the Lord are of another ſeed, ſo they are alſo of another Principle, and therefore they cannot do as others do. Principles are the ſprings of all actions, and every man acts according to his principle, according to the principle that is in him. Now he that fears the Lord, differs from another man in his principles, and ſo he doth alſo in his actions, and in his ends.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Look into his ends, and you ſhall ſee how they differ from other mens; ends are the ſeeds of actions; and if ſo, a man that fears the Lord, his ends differ from other mens; and then no wonder that he cannot, will not do as others do. Again,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, As he differs in his ends, ſo alſo in his conſcience; every man is according as his conſcience is: Take a man that fears the Lord, and he is tender of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but others that have their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces burnt and ſeared, are not ſo, and if ſo, then no wonder that he that fears the Lord cannot, will not do as others do.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:57690:50"/>
            <p>Fifthly, As he that fears the Lord dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in the the matter of his conſcience, ſo he differs alſo in the matter of his reſtraints. A wicked man abſtains it may be from one evil, to commit another, but he that fears the Lord, abſtains from all evil, becauſe of the fear of God, which the other doth not. A wicked man is bad in good company, and a good man is good in bad company, yea he is the ſame in all company; therefore he that fears the Lord cannot, will not do as others do. But,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Is it poſſible for a man that fears the Lord, to do ſometimes as others do?</p>
            <p>Yes he may: For the Apoſtle ſpeaks plainly concerning the ſame, Rom. 12.1. Mark what he ſaith; <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the mercies of God, That ye be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to this preſent world,</hi> &amp;c. But now obſerve this; That it is one thing what a man doth in a ſudden paſſion, and another thing what he doth in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſideration: For take a man that fears the Lord, and in his ſudden paſſion he ſhall deny Chriſt as well as another; but in the way of ſerious conſideration he ſhall never do it. And further take notice, that it is one thing what a man doth in a particular action, and another
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:57690:51"/>thing what he doth in his common practice, for you may find in Scripture, that Gods people have ſometimes run away from God as to a particular Action, but yet in their conſtant courſe they feared the Lord, and therefore thoſe that fear the Lord do not do as others do, becauſe if they turn aſide, they repent of their ſo doing, and turn to God again: So I ſay there is ſtill a difference between them that fear the Lord, &amp; thoſe that do not. But</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Suppoſe a man do truly fear the Lord, what is the Iſſue and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence thereof? why the Iſſue will be this: If you fear the Lord, God will deal well with you, he will deal well with you in a ſpecial manner: he will make a difference between you &amp; another in his diſpenſations. Pſal. 1. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the counſel of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, nor ſtandeth in the way of Sinners, nor ſetteth in the heat of the ſcornful; But his delight is in the law of the Lord, and in his law doth he meditate day and night; he ſhall be like a tree planted by the rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that bringeth forth its fruit in his ſeaſon, his leaſe alſo ſhall not wither, but whatſoever he doth ſhall proſper; the ungodly are not ſo, but are like unto the chaff, which the wind driveth away. Therefore the ungodly ſhall not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57690:51"/>ſtand in Judgement, nor Sinners in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Righteous; But the way of the ungodly ſhall periſh.</hi> Thus you ſee how Gods diſpenſations ſhall be to them that fear him: it ſhall go well with them, but not ſo to the wicked: It is ſaid that <hi>thoſe that feared the Lord ſpake often one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And it is ſaid in Iſa. 8.11, 12. <hi>For the Lord ſpake thus to me with a ſtrong hand, and Inſtructed me, not to walk in the way of this people, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 112.6, 7, 8. You may find there that there will be a great difference one day, between them that fear the Lord, and they that do not: <hi>Surely he ſhall not be moved for ever, the Righteous ſhall be in everlaſting remembrance. He ſhall not be afraid of evil Tydings, his heart is fixed truſting in the Lord: his heart is eſtabliſhed, he ſhall not be afraid, untill he ſee his deſire upon his enemies, he hath diſperſed, he hath given to the poor, his Righteouſneſs indureth for ever, his horn ſhall be exalted with honour: The wicked ſhall ſee it and be grieved, he ſhall gnaſh his teeth and melt away, the deſire of the wicked ſhall periſh, yea God will do great things for them that fear him: he will put his law into their Hearts, that thereby they may keep his Commandments.</hi> He will do greatly for them, for his eye ſhall be upon them. The eye of the Lord
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57690:52"/>is upon the righteous, and his ear is open to their cry. He is ready to anſwer thoſe that fear him upon all accounts. Read what the Pſalmiſt ſaith, Pſal. 31.19. <hi>O how great is thy goodneſs, which thou haſt laid up for them that fear thee, that thou haſt wrought for them that truſt in thee, before the Sons of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea further if you truly fear the Lord, The eye of God ſhall be upon you for good; unto him will I look that trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth, unto him will I look that feareth ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Again, if you truly fear the Lord, the Lord will delight in you,</p>
            <p>Yea God will be a God unto you, God will be a ſtrong Tower to you, and he will ſanctify all unto you: and to ſay no more, They that fear the Lord ſhall want no good thing: O what a bleſſed thing is it then, to fear the Lord; for from him God will with-hold no good thing: and thus you ſee the Iſſue of this fearing of God; Conſider it, conſider I ſay the conſequence and Iſſue of it, and let it be ſo many motives to ſtir you up more and more to fear the Lord.</p>
            <p>So much ſhall ſerve for the Doctrinal part: Now then by way of Application,</p>
            <p>Here we may ſee what a ſad excuſe that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:57690:52"/>will be which many make, That ſay they do but as others do, but Alas this is an excuſe fit for the lips of thoſe only, who fear not God at all. But</p>
            <p>Secondly, If this Doctrine be true, then here you may ſee who thoſe are that fear God in truth; there are many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to it; but we find here, that thoſe that truly fear the Lord cannot, will not do as others do: They will not do as others do in the matter of their choice, in the matter of their worſhip, nor of their calling, nor in what they are intruſted with, nor in their refreſhments, nor in their Afflictions, nor in their right and propriety, and if it be ſo, how few are there that fear the Lord in Truth. They that truly fear God ſay always as <hi>Nehemiah, But ſo did not I becauſe of the fear of God.</hi> There are many that lie quiet under ſins of Omiſſion, and under ſins of Commiſſion too, but ſo will not I becauſe of the fear of God: Do others ſin, and do others act contrary to the will of God, yet let us not do ſo, but let us ſay with Nehemiah, But ſo will not I becauſe of the fear of God. O therefore let me deſire all to fear the Lord, And for you that do fear the Lord, be you comforted, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort belongs to you; Everlaſting mercy
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:57690:53"/>belongs to you who fear the Lord; <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. <hi>I have loved you with an Everlaſting love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſay, I am afraid I do not fear the Lord, and ſo this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort doth not belong to me; why con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider</p>
            <p>Firſt, Do you make conſcience of what you do, doth your conſcience accuſe you or not for what you do, do you find con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience accuſe, or excuſe?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Have you not ſinned in the dark, when none could accuſe but God only, and do you Act, and walk, and live, and labour, as if you were in the preſence and ſight of God? if you do thus, then you do fear the Lord, <hi>And then it ſhall be well with you, Eccleſ.</hi> 8.12. Again</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Do you run, and ſpeak one to another, if ſo, then this is to fear the Lord, for it is ſaid that <hi>they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another,</hi> Mal. 3.16. And</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Do you truly deſire to fear the Lord, then look into Nehemiah, and obſerve his ſpirit well and do according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And to ſay no more,</p>
            <p>Have you had advantages to make you rich in this world, and would you not take them, becauſe of the fear of God,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57690:53"/>then certainly you have received free grace, and you have the Spirit of God, for this is a true ſign, that you have true grace in your hearts; and that you are one of them that truly fear the Lord: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be you comforted, for comfort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs unto you, everlaſting mercy belongs unto you.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſay: Suppoſe I do not fear the Lord, what ſhall I do that I may fear the Lord, fear him as I ſhould do, fear him more and more.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, If you would fear the Lord in truth. Then</p>
            <p>Firſt, Be humbled for want of this fear: That man is not far from grace, who is humbled for the want of grace; a man will never be humbled for unbelief; unleſs he be humbled for the want of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Go to God and beg of him to fulfil his promiſe, God hath ſaid, <hi>I will put my fear into their hearts;</hi> Now go to God I ſay and beg, and deſire him that he would make good this promiſe to you.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you would fear God in truth, then obſerve what that is, that is neereſt, and deareſt to you, and give that up to God. You know <hi>Abraham</hi> offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up <hi>Iſaac,</hi> his only <hi>Son,</hi> and ſaith God,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:57690:54"/>
               <hi>By this I know thou feareſt me.</hi> And further</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If you would fear the Lord in Truth, then worſhip God, according to his own appointment, take heed of mingling of Gods worſhip with any of mans Inventions, for he that doth ſo fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not God, nor worſhippeth him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own appointment. And then</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If you would fear the Lord in Truth, then take heed of ſinning when you have an opportunity, Again</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If you would fear God more, than love the Lord more, labour to ſtrengthen your love to God. Again</p>
            <p>Seventhly, If you would have your fear ſtrengthned more, and more, then ſtudy much the free grace of God, in giving out his mercy to one, more than to another, <hi>Two in a field, the one taken and the other left, Two walking together, the one taken, and the other left,</hi> If you would ſtrengthen your fear, ſtudy much the free grace of God.</p>
            <p>Eightly, If you would fear the Lord in Truth, Live much in, and ſtudy much upon, dependance wholly upon God, it is our great duty to depend upon God.</p>
            <p>If a man be upon a high Tower, and another holds him from falling by the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57690:54"/>hand only, he will certainly be very fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of offending him that holds him ſo: why we are thus in the hand of God, and our dependance is upon him for every thing, how fearful ought we then to be of offending this God, O ſtudy your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God more and more; and</p>
            <p>Again, Uſe the world as uſing it not: deal with men as in the preſence of God, and when you are dealing with men, be ſure to deal with God before all the men of the world.</p>
            <p>Again, Let your eye be very much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Severity and Juſtice of God, upon his ſeverity and Juſtice, conſider Gods ſevereneſs to <hi>Adam</hi> in eating the forbidden fruit, and his ſevereneſs to <hi>Moſes</hi> for a word, that for one word God would not let him enter into the promiſed land, and conſider his ſeverity to <hi>David</hi> for numbring the people. Yea</p>
            <p>Again conſider, That God cannot only deſtroy the body, but ſoul and body too. Therefore O man fear him that can <hi>deſtroy both body and ſoul when he will in Hell fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus now if you would have your fear ſtrengthened, then ſtudy theſe things, conſider and meditate upon theſe things. But yet a little further</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:57690:55"/>
            <p>If you would ſtrengthen your fear of God more and more, then labour after more Communion with him now, in this world while you are here, we uſe to ſay <hi>Too much familiarity breeds contempt,</hi> but here it is not ſo, for by familiarity and communion with God, we ſhall have more ſweetneſs, and more delight in his wayes, more ſtrength in his ſervice, more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in our afflictions: If you would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have theſe advantages, then labour to walk more cloſe with God, and to have more communion with him; labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay to have more communion with God, if you would fear him more and more: The greater a perſon is here on Earth (as I told you before) the more we fear him, and the nearer he is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to us, the more we reverence him.</p>
            <p>My Friends, would you obtain ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting mercy, would you have everlaſting mercy belong to you, then labour to fear the Lord in truth yet more and more, and I beſeech you to think of this Truth, meditate upon it, think of it upon all occaſions, and ſay, do others ſlubber over duties, ſo will not I, becauſe I fear the Lord; do others walk injuriouſly, ſo will not I, becauſe I fear the Lord; do
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57690:55"/>others do contrary to the will of God, but ſo will not I, becauſe I fear the Lord: Let this truth go up and down with you, and it will keep you in your dealing both with God and man: Remember the Charecter of one that fears the Lord, He is one that cannot, will not do as others do, for ſo ſaith the Text: <hi>But ſo did not I, becauſe of the fear of God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:57690:56"/>
            <head>SERMON. V.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 133.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold how good and how pleaſant it is, for brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this ſhort Pſalm, we may ſee the excellency of the Saints Communion, fellowſhip, and Brotherly Agreement.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>Deſcribed</hi> and <hi>Commended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Deſcribed from the fountain of it, from God as a Father, and therefore he ſayes, <hi>How good and how pleaſant it is for Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Deſcribed alſo from the Act and Exerciſe thereof, <hi>which is to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It is commended, from the goodneſs, and profitableneſs, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs of it, It is a good thing, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable thing for brethren to dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Unity, behold how good it is in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57690:56"/>the eyes of men, behold how pleaſant it is beyond expreſſion, <hi>for brethren to dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the goodneſs and pleaſantneſs of it is expreſt by two ſimilitudes: It is compared to the precious Oyntment upon the head of <hi>Aaron,</hi> verſe 2. <hi>It is like the precious Oyntment upon the head, that run down upon the beard; even</hi> Aarons <hi>heard, that went down to the skirts of his garment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is compared alſo to the dew that fell upon Hermon, and the hills of Zion, verſe 3. <hi>As the dew of Hermon, and as the dew that deſcended upon the mountains of Zion, &amp;c.</hi> Thus you ſee the deſign of this Pſalm, is to declare the goodneſs, and profitableneſs of Unity between bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, from whence then I take up this Obſervation;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a loving agreement between the Saints, among themſelves is exceeding pleaſant, and very profitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some things are pleaſant, but not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and ſome things are profitable and not Pleaſant, as Phyſick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and fellowſhip and a loving agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among the Saints is both pleaſant and profitable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is a pleaſant thing for the Saints, and people of God to agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:57690:57"/>for the ſame word which is uſed here for <hi>pleaſant,</hi> is uſed alſo in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew for a Harmony of Muſick, ſuch as when they riſe to the higheſt ſtrains of the Violl, when the ſtrings are all put in order, to make up a Harmony, ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant is it, ſuch pleaſantneſs is there in the Saints Agreement.</p>
            <p>The ſame word is uſed alſo in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew for the pleaſantneſs of a corn-field, when a field is clothed with corn, though it be cut down, yet it is very pleaſant, O how pleaſant is it, and ſuch is the Saints agreement.</p>
            <p>The ſame word in the Pſalmiſt is uſed alſo for the ſweetneſs of honey, and of ſweet things, in oppoſition to bitter things; And thus you ſee the pleaſantneſs of it, by its being compared to the Harmony of Muſick, to the corn-field, to the ſweetneſs of honey, to the precious Oyntment that ran down <hi>Aarons</hi> beard, and to the dew that fell upon Hermon and the Hills of Zion: and all this is to diſcover the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs, profitableneſs, and ſweetneſs of the Saints Agreement. <hi>Behold how good and how pleaſant it is, &amp;c.</hi> It is a pleaſant thing to behold the Sun, but it is much more pleaſant to behold the Saints Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Unity among themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:57690:57"/>
            <p>There are many times breakings and loſings in the love of the Saints, and therefore when they come to an agreement and union among themſelves again, it muſt needs be very pleaſant and profitable, and ſweet, for things once loſt and found again are very ſweet; And upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it is, that the Commandment of love is called <hi>a new Commandment,</hi> becauſe it is broken ſo often, and ſo often renewed again: And the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks here of the ſweetneſs and pleaſantneſs of Unity, becauſe there is no ſweetneſs in diviſion, but Unity is a good way and means to keep out trouble, and evil diviſion from among a people. And</p>
            <p>Further, the more difficulty any mercy is obtained with, the ſweeter it is when obtained; there are many things which are hard to come by, but when they are obtained they are ſweet, and ſo there are many difficulties in the way of love and ſweet agreement, and the people of God are incumbred with many difficulties, they have many things to put them out of the way of love, and of ſweet agreement among themſelves; and therefore ſaith the Apoſtle Phil. 1.27. <hi>Only let your Converſation be as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt, that whether I come and ſee you, or
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:57690:58"/>elſe be abſent, I may hear of your affairs, that you ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one mind ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, The more ſuitable any thing is to our condition, the more pleaſant and ſweet it is: Now this brotherly love and union, is a conjunction of ſuitable things, and is ſuitable to our condition, and ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things are delightful unto men, and the more ſuitable any thing is, the more we delight in it: And this agreement, this union, is every way ſuitable to our own condition as we are <hi>men,</hi> and is alſo ſuitable to all the creatures, for they run together, and agree together; And it is ſuitable to us alſo as we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> it is ſuitable to Chriſts command; <hi>A new command ſaith he. I give unto you, that you love one another.</hi> It is ſuitable to Chriſts own example, who hath loved us; and ſuitable alſo to the Goſpel, which is a Goſpel of peace: <hi>Let your converſation be as becometh the Goſpel, that you be of one ſpirit, and of one mind:</hi> So I ſay, this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreement is every way ſuitable, and therefore the more pleaſant and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and ſo it ought to be unto us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As it is pleaſant and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſo it is a profitable good: <hi>Behold how good a thing it is,</hi> it is very profitable.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:57690:58"/>For is it not profitable for the <hi>dew to fall upon</hi> Hermon, <hi>and upon the hills of</hi> Zion, <hi>to make them fruitfull?</hi> Why, ſuch is the dew of holy agreement, when it falls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hearts of men: And this doth make men increaſe, and multiply in the Church, and to be fruitful in good works; the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>God commandeth his bleſſing;</hi> and when God bleſſeth, we ſhall certainly increaſe and multiply; and this I ſay did increaſe the Church, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by are the Saints both increaſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted by the bleſſing of God on them, they do increaſe in things that are good, and profitable; and this was the thing which Chriſt prayed for, yea prayed for again and again; yea as I ſaid it is the great thing which Chriſt hath commanded: <hi>A new command,</hi> &amp;c. Is it not therefore good and profitable to love one another?</p>
            <p>Again, This is the mercy and the grace that is promiſed, ſpecially in the latter times glorious things are ſpoken of, and promiſed to the laſt daies; and this is one of thoſe things which are promiſed, and if ſo, it is then certainly good, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
            <p>Again, This is the Legacy which Chriſt left with his diſciples and people; ſaith he, <hi>Peace I leave with you, my peace I give
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:57690:59"/>unto you, not as the world giveth, give I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you,</hi> John 14.27. and therefore ſurely this agreement among brethren is very good and profitable.</p>
            <p>Again, Certainly it is good, and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to walk worthy of the high calling, to which Chriſt hath called us, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, Eph. 4.1, 2, 3. <hi>I beſeech you to walk worthy of the vocation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ye are called, with all lowlineſs and meekneſs, with long ſuffering, forbearing one another in love, endeavouring to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Again, Is it not good and profitable that our prayers ſhould be heard, that God ſhould hear and grant our requeſts and prayers? Why, look into the Scriptures, and you will find that our love is a help to our prayers; it is a help unto us, whereby to have our prayers heard and anſwered.</p>
            <p>Again, Is it not good and profitable for a man to know that he is a child of God, and that he hath an intereſt in Chriſt? Why, look into 1 John 3.14. <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death unto life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we love the brethren:</hi> There is a day of death, of natural death, whereby man ſhall paſs from life to death; and there is likewiſe a time of ſpiritual life; when a man paſſeth from death to life. Now
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:57690:59"/>how ſhall I know whether I am <hi>paſſed from death to life? Why, if I love the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Yea ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Hereby ſhall all know that you are my diſciples, if you love one another;</hi> not only your ſelves ſhall know it, but others ſhall know it alſo; and is it not then very good, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? For hereby you ſhall know that your prayers are heard; and by this alſo you ſhall know that you are paſſed from death to life; and hereby you ſhall not only know your ſelves to be Chriſts diſciples, but others ſhall know it alſo: and if it be ſo, then certainly it muſt be good and profitable.</p>
            <p>Again, This will give a reliſh and a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to all your injoyments; it is the ſalt of all your comforts: <hi>Have ſalt in your ſelves, and have peace one with another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although our condition be never ſo proſperous, yet if we cannot agree among our ſelves, if love and peace be wanting, that ſowrs all the reſt; and though the ordinances be never ſo ſweet, and our priviledges never ſo many, yet if we be not united together in love, all is made ſowre; this is that which ſowrs all our enjoyments, the want of love, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for that gives a reliſh to all our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments when we have it.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:57690:60"/>
            <p>Again, This is that which will make all things eaſie unto you, though they be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo hard in themſelves; whereas the contrary will make all things hard though never ſo eaſie: If I am to do a work or a ſervice for one: why, though the work be never ſo hard of it ſelf, yet love will make it eaſie; many complain and ſay they cannot profit by the Ordinances: why, what is the reaſon? It is for want of love to them; there are jarrs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions between friend and friend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this man and the other man; why, it is for want of love: Love would make all things eaſie for you, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo hard. Now put all theſe things together, and then you may ſee, what a pleaſant and profitable thing it is, for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to dwell together in unity, to love, to unite, to live in unity one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Well then if this be ſo, why ſhould we not all abound in it? why do not we love and agree one with another, if it be ſo good and profitable as we have heard, then let us all agree together.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſay, we do live together in love and unity, and we are united one to another, But</p>
            <p>Firſt, Yet give me leave to mind you
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:57690:60"/>of what the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 Theſſ. 4.9. <hi>But as touching brotherly love, you need not that I write unto you; for you your ſelves are taught of God to love one another, and indeed ye do it towards all the brethren which are in all</hi> Macedonia; <hi>but we beſeech you brethren that you increaſe more and more.</hi> Though you do it, yet we beſeech you to increaſe it more and more, and ſo I ſay to you: yea and Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it alſo, and you muſt do it in obedience to his command.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If our love be right as it ſhould be, then we ſhall love others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, even our neighbours and friends and brethren; we ſhall love them as our ſelves. <hi>The ſecond Commandment</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>is like unto it, that you love your neighbour as your ſelf.</hi> Pray for your ſelves, do all the good you can for your ſelves, avoid all iniquity that may come upon your ſelves, and to prove your love to be right, do all this for your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours alſo, and love them as your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If our love be as it ſhould be, we ſhall then love others, becauſe they are godly, let them be of this opinion, or of the other opinion, yet that matters not; though they be not of my opinion, yet if my love be right, I love them becauſe they are god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:57690:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>and I love him moſt that is moſt godly; and as his increaſeth godlineſs, ſo muſt my love increaſe toward him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If your love be true, and ſuch as it ought to be, then you will love one another, and love your brother; as Chriſt loved you, even ſo ought you to love one another; how was that? why, Chriſt loved you freely, in oppoſition to all the injuries you had done unto him: It is ſaid, 1 Joh. 1.6, 7. <hi>If we ſay we have fellowſhip with him, and walk in darkneſs, we lie and do not the truth; but if we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one with another:</hi> and in John 3.16. <hi>For God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten ſon.</hi> Yea Chriſt hath ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us, that he hath laid down his life for us; and we are to love as Chriſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, even to the laying down of our lives for our brethren.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If your love be true, it ought to be without reſtriction, yea and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all diſſimulation: I ſay you are to love without any reſtriction, the only meaſure of love is to know no meaſure; and you are to love without any diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, yea and your love ought to be alſo without degeneration; many do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to love ſpiritually, but end carnally;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:57690:61"/>but true love is without reſtriction, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation, or degeneration.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If your love be true, and ſuch as it ought to be, then it will never be bought, neither can it be ſold; Love can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be bought, and if it be true love, it will never be ſold, neither directly nor indirectly.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, If your love be as it ought to be, it will be ſingular, it will make you ſingular in your love: <hi>Love your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſaith Chriſt; It hath been ſaid you ſhall hate your enemies, and love your neighbours,</hi> but I ſay unto you love them both, <hi>love your enemies, do good to them that hate you, and deſpightfully uſe you; for if you love them that love you what reward have you, do not even the Publicans ſo,</hi> Mat. 5.43, 44, 45. Love them that hate you, this is ſingular love; and love where it is true, will make a man thus ſingular in his ways and carriage.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, True love is a praying love. Saies one, <hi>I never loved any man, till I had prayed for him in particular:</hi> true love I ſay is a praying love.</p>
            <p>And true love is a love at all times, at one time as well as another.</p>
            <p>And a man that loves truly, declares that he is looſned from the world, and that he is one that is wrought upon by
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:57690:62"/>the Holy Ghoſt: In the Primitive times, it was ſaid that they were all of one heart, and all things were common among them; and when we are thus of one heart and of one mind; it doth declare that we have been wrought upon by the Holy Ghoſt; and therefore certainly, there is a great miſtake in mens love, all men ſay they love the ſaints; they love them in words, though I am afraid many love them but little in their hearts.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, how far is our love to be exerciſed, <hi>upon whom,</hi> and <hi>how farr?</hi> I ſay no more but this, ſo far as the word <hi>Brethren</hi> doth extend, ſo far this union and love ought to go, <hi>Behold how good and how pleaſant it is for Brethren to dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unity.</hi> So far I ſay, as this word brethren extends; and that is ſo far, as God is their Father, it matters not for opinion, or what judgement they are of; if God be their Father, they are your brethren, and are to be beloved by you, and ſo far is your love to reach and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay wherein doth this love conſiſt?</p>
            <p>Why, in theſe three things.</p>
            <p>In the matter of our judgements.</p>
            <p>In the matter of our Affections.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:57690:62"/>
            <p>In the matter of our Practice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In the matter of our <hi>Judgements.</hi> Rom. 12.16. <hi>Be of the ſame mind one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, mind not high things, but condiſcend to men of low eſtate; Be not wiſe in your own conceit, recompence no man evil for evil; if it be poſſible as much as in you lieth, live peaceably with all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, In the matter of our <hi>Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> in the 10. verſe of this Chapter. <hi>Be kindly affectioned one towards another with brotherly love, in honour preferring one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, In the matter of our <hi>Practice, read the</hi> 3. <hi>verſe of this Chapter, For I ſay through the grace given unto me, to every man that is among you, not to think of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more highly than he ought to think; but to think ſoberly, according as God hath dealt to every man the meaſure of faith.</hi> Thus you ſee how we ſhould act, as to our Judgements, Affections, and Practices, one toward another.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay if this be ſo, then how much is our love wanting one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward another, but what ſhall we do, that our love to one another may be more knit together; what ſhall we do that we may advance, and riſe to this holy agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both in our own hearts and others?</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:57690:63"/>
            <p>For anſwer hereunto, take theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Be ſerious in this work, and lay aſide the former hinderances of your love, and your former diviſions; and let not any of you ſay, this is the fault, and that is the fault, and ſuch a one is the cauſe of it, and ſuch a one is the occaſion of it: No, but lay the ſault on your ſelves, lay it upon your ſelves, and not upon others, and ſay, <hi>It is I, the Lord knows it is I; it is I that have raiſed this ſtorm; and ſay as</hi> David, <hi>I have ſinned, I have ſinned.</hi> Let not your former diviſions be forgotten, but take warning by them; lay not the fault I ſay upon others, but upon your ſelves, and acknowledge it and ſay; It is I, I Lord that have ſinned. And,</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you do deſire to be ſerious in this work, then do you deſire Peace; and if it be poſſible live at peace with all men: the ſame word that is uſed in the original for Perſecutors, is alſo uſed for peace, to ſhew that we ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after it with might and main, as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors follow thoſe they perſecute; and that if poſſible we ſhould live at peace with all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Be ſure you ſtrengthen your love; Love muſt be ſtrengthned, elſe this
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:57690:63"/>union cannot continue; it is the property of love to interpret love in the beſt ſence, to interpret things well.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is the property of love to ſpeak highly of the perſon, or thing belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; where there is an uniting, and a ſweet agreement, there love will ſpeak high things of each other.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The property of love is to cover the infirmities of thoſe they love; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed how can there be any agreement, if infirmities be not covered: It is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of love to give no offence, nor to take any; and it is a great ſign that there is no agreement, nor no love, when people are ſo apt to give offence, and to take offence; for true love is apt to do nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but to take all in good part.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, True love knows how to give and how to take admonitions: And thus you have heard what love will do; therefore I beſeech you to ſtrengthen your love to one another; yea I beſeech you in the Lord to increaſe it more and more, one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward another.</p>
            <p>But you may ſay further, ſuppoſe there be a difference in the matter of our Judgements or opinions: what ſhall we do to remove it? Why,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Be ſure of this, that you do not
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:57690:64"/>miſtake the meaning of that Scripture, which your judgement is founded upon. It is ſaid <hi>There was a diviſion among the people becauſe of Chriſt;</hi> why for what was it, what was the reaſon of it? It was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of miſunderſtanding, and for want of a right underſtanding of Chriſt: So I ſay, this diviſion may come for want of a right underſtanding of the Scriptures, upon which our judgement is grounded and founded. But</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider O man whether you do not ſettle your judgement upon the judgement, or opinion of any, or upon the knowledge of another: <hi>Haſt thou faith ſaith</hi> the Apoſtle, <hi>have it to thy ſelf before God;</hi> Rom. 14.22. But is not a man then to confeſs his faith before others, when he is called to it? Yes, But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks here of leſſer things; if thou haſt faith have it to thy ſelf in little diſputable things; and do not rely upon others, but look to thy ſelf, and give things a time; <hi>in due time God will reveal,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if you deſire this holy agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then do what you can to keep uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Miniſtry, and between the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. It was not for nothing that our Saviour prayed, John 17.11, 21. <hi>Holy
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:57690:64"/>Father keep through thine own name, thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they may be one as we are; That they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us.</hi> It is not good for people to cry, <hi>I am for</hi> Paul, <hi>and I am for</hi> Apollo, <hi>and I am for</hi> Cephas, and the like, this is the way to make diviſion; therefore do all you can to live in love and unity; for love is of God, and the contrary is of the Devil.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Take heed of diſputation, what have we got this many years by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation? thoſe that are weak, are ſooner brought in by humiliation, than by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If after all this there do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main diviſion among you, by reaſon of your judgements, or opinions; then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Apoſtles rule, and be ſure to walk by it: for ſaith he (as we inſtanced before) <hi>Let no man think more highly of himſelf than he ought to think, but to think ſoberly; as God hath dealt to every man the meaſure of faith.</hi> The Apoſtle directs us, to live humbly, and walk meekly one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward another; and not to be raſh, or to think highly of our ſelves. But fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If we would live in love and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:57690:65"/>unity, then let us look upon other mens infirmities in conjunction with their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, and their excellencies in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with their infirmities; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the one will take away or hide the other: Let us not pore only upon a mans infirmities, upon his <hi>Euts</hi> as I may ſay; he is a godly man but —: therefore if you would agree, joyn his infirmities and his excellencies together, and then look upon him.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, If you ſhould meet with any provocation, that may weaken your love one toward another, then be ſure to take that as an opportunity to exerciſe your patience, and your love; when you meet a beggar in the ſtreets full of ſores, then you think you have an opportunity to exerciſe your charity, to give ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And ſo you ſhould ſay, when you are provoked by another to debilitate your love and affection, you may ſay, why now have I an opportunity to exerciſe my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. Again</p>
            <p>Eighthly, If you will live in love and unity, then you muſt reſolve, with the grace of God, to love, where you are not beloved; let love riſe above all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; labour for a Goſpel ſpirit, to love though you are not loved: A Legal ſpirit
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:57690:65"/>is a fretful ſpirit, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>you know not of what ſpirit you are of;</hi> labour I ſay after a Goſpel ſpirit, yea the ſpirit of Chriſt <hi>who was as a Lamb, he opened not his mouth:</hi> if you would live in love and unity, then take heed of a Legal ſpirit, and labour after this Goſpel ſpirit. Again</p>
            <p>Ninthly, If you would agree together, and live in love and unity; then be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for the want of love to one another, and take heed for the future of thoſe things that hinder your love one toward another, there are four or five of them, obſerve them and take heed of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Pride,</hi> A proud man is much gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to contention.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Paſſion,</hi> For though a man diſlikes, and is ſorry for what he hath done in his paſſion, when it is over, and though what he doth in his paſſion be one thing, and what he doth in his ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration is another thing; yet we are to take great heed of paſſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Another enemy to love is <hi>ſtrangeneſs,</hi> ſtrangeneſs ends in enmity; when brethren and friends grow ſtrangers one to another, then they ſurmiſe things one of another; and that deſtroys love and unity.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Another is <hi>deſigning one againſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:57690:66"/>another;</hi> true love knows no deſigns up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others; no man can endure to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns laid againſt him; deſigning cauſeth anger, enmity and hatred, and hinders true love one toward another.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Another is <hi>whiſpering, a whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſeparateth true friends,</hi> Pro. 16.28. But now if any one ſhould come to me, and tell me any thing againſt a brother, I would not believe the whiſperer, till I had ſpoken with the other; for a cauſe can never be truly known, nor judged of, till both parties have been heard ſpeak: Thus you may ſee the five things that hinder love, that is Pride, Paſſion, Strangeneſs, deſigning one upon another, and heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto whiſperers. Now as you deſire to live in love and unity, obſerve theſe things, and take heed of them.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, Let me ſay to you (holy and beloved brethren) if you would love one another, then forgive one another, and live more unto God who loveth you, live more to God, leſt he ſhould turn his love to hatred and wrath againſt you.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Strengthen your love to God himſelf, the more love you have to God, the more will you love others.</p>
            <p n="12">12. If you would live in love and Unity, then you muſt willingly take wrong,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:57690:66"/>and give up your right for peace ſake, and for agreement: ſaith <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Lot, Let there be no difference between my heardmen and thy heardmen, for we are brethren;</hi> Now <hi>Abraham</hi> was the elder, and therefore it was his right to have the choice, but yet for peace ſake he gives up his right, and ſayes to <hi>Lot, Take what you will, the right hand or the left:</hi> there was a diviſion between them, and the Cananites were in the land, and therefore it was no good time for them to be at difference one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: when the Cananites were in the land, it was no good time then for good men to ſtrive, and therefore <hi>Abraham</hi> for peace ſake gives up his right: ſo I ſay for peace ſake and for a holy agreement, you ſhould willingly give up your right, and render up your own right to preſerve peace and Unity one with another; O friends, love one another that you may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare your ſelves to be heavenly children, to be children of your heavenly Father, conſider, Phil. 1.27. <hi>Only let your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation be as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt; that whether I come or be abſent, I may hear of your affairs, that you ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one mind ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O friends, let me beſeech you to love
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:57690:67"/>one another, and to take all advantages that may increaſe your love, how can you ſhew your face, before the free love and grace of God, if you do not love one another; with what face can you go to God for free grace and love, when you your ſelves have no love for your brethren.</p>
            <p>If a poor man ſhould do a rich man a great deal of prejudice, and if this rich man ſhould nevertheleſs invite this poor man to a feaſt, and welcome him, and do him abundance of good, would you not ſay that this is wonderful love and kindneſs, becauſe the poor man is no way able to gratify him, or to make any requital for what he receives, but only by thankfulneſs; it may be he may be thankful to him: why thus it is with us now, this is our own caſe, for we have done great injury to God, and yet God hath loved us, and hath given us bleſſings and riches, and what doth he expect for it all, ſurely no reward from us, for he knows we are poor and not able to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy him, no he expects nothing, but only that we ſhould love one another; ſaies God, you can do nothing for me, all that I deſire is, that you would love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Truth; How then, I ſay, will you be able to ſhew your faces before the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:57690:67"/>God of heaven, if you love not one Another.</p>
            <p>O look after this love, which is ſo much commended in this little Pſalm, O how ſweet, and perfuming it is, it is as ſweet as honey, <hi>is is like unto the Oyl that ran down</hi> Aarons <hi>beard, like the dew upon Hermon, and as the dew that fell down upon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Zion;</hi> yea this is that which is ſweet and profitable, that which will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume you; now if you do deſire that Gods perfumes may come upon you, and that the dew of Gods bleſſings may fall upon you, labour more and more to love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and let not love be wanting; I cannot tell how it may be with you, yet let me deſire you, as you would honour your ſelves now, and as you deſire hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in this life, and alſo to be bleſſed hereafter to all Eternity, obſerve this <hi>new Commandment</hi> to love one another; and as you do deſire to declare that you have received free grace, and that you have that ſeal, with which God ſeals the ſoul for his own, to live with him for ever, be exhorted to be of one mind, and love one another, <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord, and be of one mind;</hi> be united one to another, and let your hearts abound in love more and more one toward another.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:57690:68"/>
            <head>SERMON VI.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MICAH. 6.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lords voice cryeth unto the City, and the man of Wiſdom ſhall ſee thy name, hear ye the rod and who hath appointed it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>MEthinks I ſee a great rod, ready to be layd upon the back of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I would therefore at this time endeavour to inform you what the voice of this Rod is, and have to that end choſen this Scripture to ſpeak unto.</p>
            <p>In this Chapter then you have Gods controverſy with his own people; ſet down at the end of the 2. verſe. <hi>For the Lord hath a controverſy with his people, and he will plead with Iſrael;</hi> And then he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them with</p>
            <p>Firſt, Unthankfulneſs for many years in the 3.4. &amp; 5. verſes, <hi>O my people what have I done unto thee, and wherewith have
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:57690:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>have I done unto thee, and wherewith have I wearied thee, teſtifie againſt me, for I brought thee up out of the land of Egypt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He Chargeth them with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, and ſhews them the evill of it, in the 6. and 7. verſes, <hi>Will the Lord be pleaſed with thouſands of rams,</hi> &amp;c. And then</p>
            <p>Thirthly, He pleades againſt them in the 8. verſe. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee O man what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtice and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi> And then</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He ſeals up the Sentence in this verſe of my Text. <hi>The Lords voice cryeth unto the City, and the man of Wiſdom ſhall ſee thy name, hear ye the rod and who hath appointed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein you have three things eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially remarkable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The people the Lords voice cryeth unto, and that is unto the City, <hi>the Lords voice cryeth unto the City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, You have en exhortation to hear the voice of the Rod. <hi>Hear ye the rod and who hath appointed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, You have an Argument to preſs you ſo to do; <hi>It is your wiſdom, the man of wiſdom ſhall ſee thy name. The Lords voice cryeth unto the City,</hi> that is unto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, and Jeruſalem, the Chief Cities:
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:57690:69"/>
               <hi>And the man of wiſdom ſhall ſee thy name:</hi> The diſpenſations of God in the way of his mercy or Juſtice are his <hi>name:</hi> As a man is known by his name, ſo God is known by his diſpenſations, which though they be dark to the world, yet the man of wiſdom ſhall ſee them and diſcern them: <hi>Therefore hear ye the Rod, and who hath appointed it</hi> the Rod; that is the Rod of Correction, Now there is</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Rod of power and dignity, <hi>He ſhall ſend his rod out of Zion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a rod of Diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: Ezek. 20.37. <hi>I will cauſe you to paſs under the Rod, and I will bring you under the bond of the Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is the rod of direction: <hi>Thy rod and thy ſtaff they ſhall comfort me,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, There is a rod of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both Eccleſiaſtical and civil: As for Eccleſiaſtical ſaith Paul, <hi>ſhall I come unto you with a rod,</hi> and as for civil, <hi>he that ſpareth the rod hateth the Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, There is a rod of Deſtruction, <hi>thou ſhalt break them with a Rod of Iron, and daſh them to peices like a potters veſſel, Pſalm</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p>Now it is a rod of Correction that we are to underſtand here, from whence I take up this Obſervation.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:57690:69"/>
            <p>That when God viſits the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his people with a rod, it is their beſt wiſdom to hear the rod, and who hath appointed it; It is their true Intereſt and beſt wiſdom ſo to do.</p>
            <p>For the opening and cleering hereof, I ſhall ſpeak to theſe 4. or 5. Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That God doth not ſteal upon a people with his Judgements, but he firſt warns them before he ſmites them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When God ſmites his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he deals with them in the way of rod.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That Gods Rod is a teaching Rod.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That the meſſage of the Rod is commonly ſent to the great Cities, and to the great Towns of a Nation or people.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, when God ſmites his own people with the rod, it is their beſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and their duty to hear the rod, and who hath appointed it,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Though God conſumes a Nation at once, and deſtroys a Nation at once at laſt; Yet he ſtill doth, and will, warn a people before he deſtroys them, God will not ſteal upon a people with his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but he firſt warns them, before he conſumes them: he hath his murdering peices which he will diſcharg in due time, but he will firſt diſcharg his warning
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:57690:70"/>peices: And God doth ſometimes warn people by his word, and ſometime by his works and diſpenſations, Ezek. 33.2. <hi>Son of man ſpeak unto the Children of thy people and ſay unto them, if I bring a ſword upon the Land,</hi> &amp;c. And at the 7. verſe he applies it. So ſaith he, <hi>Thou O Son of man I have ſet thee for a watchman, unto the houſe of Iſrael; therefore thou ſhall hear the word from my mouth, and warn them from me;</hi> would you know what this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, why it is a warning by the word,</p>
            <p>Sometimes God warns his people by his works and diſpenſations, by his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon others, and by his Afflictions upon themſelves, he brings a leſſer Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prevent a greater; it is with the works of God as it with his word: Now God doth ſometimes hew down men by the word, yea he hews them down by the Miniſtry of the word; there is a time when God will hew down ſinners by the Miniſtry of the word, and lays them upon the ground a drying (as I may ſay) for Hell, before they come there; Matt. 3. <hi>The tree that bringeth not forth fruit, is hewn down and caſt into the fire,</hi> Hoſea. 6.5. <hi>Therefore I have hewed them by the Prophets, I have ſlain them by the words of my mouth,</hi> &amp;c. There is a time of hewing down, a time
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:57690:70"/>when God will hew men down by the miniſtry of the word, and as he doth thus by his word, ſo he doth the ſame alſo by his works and diſpenſations; and though God may, and can deſtroy a people at once, yet he will not ſieſe upon them before he warn them: that is the firſt proproſition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When God ſmites his own people he deals with them in the way of the Rod, though he puniſh others with Scorpious, yet ſaith he, for you that are in Covenant with me, if you ſin <hi>I will viſit your trangreſſions with a Rod:</hi> look what worldly Afflictions come upon the Saints they are ſtruck with the Rod; what greater afflictions do you read of, than what fell upon <hi>Job,</hi> why yet it was the ſtroke of the Rod, Job 9.34. <hi>Let him take away his Rod from me;</hi> when God deals with his people I ſay, he deals with them in the way of the Rod, and if you aſk the reaſon, why God uſes the rod with his own people, I anſwer,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe they are his own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Heb. 12.7, 8. <hi>If you indure cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement God deals with you as with children, if you be without chaſtiſement you are baſtards and not Sons. I know no better Argument againſt the Church of Rome</hi> ſaith Luther, <hi>than this, that ſhe reigns without the Croſs.</hi>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:57690:71"/>If two children are fighting together, and a man comes and parts them, and ſtrikes one of them, and not the other, you will preſently imagine that the Child which he ſtrikes is his own; and ſo if you ask why God uſeth the rod to his people, I anſwer, becauſe they are his own Children. And</p>
            <p>Secondly, As they are Children, ſo he loves them, and he that ſpareth the Rod hateth the Child: Now God doth not hate his Children, <hi>for every ſon that he loveth he chaſtiſeth,</hi> God loves his children, and therefore he deals with them in the way of the Rod.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is <hi>much folly bound up in the heart of a child, but the rod of Correction bringeth it out</hi> ſaith Solomon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God doth ſometimes correct his people becauſe of their folly.</p>
            <p>Why do School-Maſters uſe the Rod but only to make children learn their leſſons; if they would learn without, he would not uſe the Rod; and why doth God uſe the Rod with his people but to learn them their leſſons; for theſe reaſons therefore doth God uſe the rod with his people.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay; doth not God uſe the Rod with the wicked too, do not they come under the rod as well as the righteous.</p>
            <p>I anſwer: Solomon ſaith <hi>the Rod is for the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:57690:71"/>back of the fool,</hi> and wicked men are called ſools in Scripture, God doth ſometimes chaſtiſe the Godly by the wicked, the wicked are the rod in Gods hand, and ſometimes again, God doth puniſh wicked men by the Saints, the Saints being the rod in Gods hand: Sometimes I ſay wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men are the rod for the Godly: <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 10.5. <hi>O Aſſyrian the rod of mine anger, and the ſtaff of their hand is mine indignation.</hi> And ſometimes the Godly, are the Rod of God, in the hand of God, for puniſhing the wicked, Jer. 51.19, 20. <hi>The portion of Jacob is not like them, for he is the former of all things, and Iſrael is the rod of his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, the Lord of Hoſts is his name: Thou art my battle Axe and weapons of War, for with thee will I break in peices the Nations, and with thee will I deſtroy Kingdoms.</hi> So I ſay, as the Lord whips the ſaints by the wicked, ſo he alſo laſhes the wicked by the Godly, they being the rod in the hand of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, is there no difference between theſe two?</p>
            <p>I anſwer yes, for 1. There is a whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping rod, a rod of correction, and there is alſo a breaking rod; a whipping rod for the Saints, and a breaking rod for the wicked. In the 2. Pſalm it is ſaid, <hi>Thou will rule them with a rod of Iron, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:57690:72"/>break them in pieces like a potters veſſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Though God doth Afflict his own people with the rod, the wicked being the rod in Gods hand, yet he will caſt that rod into the ſire, when he hath done with it, but though he doth alſo puniſh the tranſgreſſions of the wicked by the righteous, they being the rod in Gods hand, yet will he not caſt that rod alſo into the fire upon that Account: the Saints may rejoyce when they ſee the wicked punſhed, becauſe they know that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhall not be thrown into the fire, but the wicked have no cauſe to rejoyce when they ſee the Godly afflicted, becauſe they may be ſure, they themſelves ſhall be thrown into the fire, when they have done their work; The Child may laugh when he ſees the rod thrown into the fire, becauſe he knows he ſhall not be thrown in himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Though God doth viſit the tranſgreſſions of his people with a Rod, yet it is a Rod that Chaſtizeth <hi>in meaſure,</hi> as you may find Iſaiah 27.7, 8. <hi>Hath he ſmitten him, as he ſmote thoſe that ſmote him, or is he ſlain according to the ſlaughter of them that are ſlain by him? In meaſure when it ſhooteth forth thou wilt debate with it, he ſtayeth his rough wind, in the day of the Eaſt-wind: and ſo in Pſalm</hi> 89.31, 32.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:57690:72"/>
               <hi>If his Children forſake my Law, then will I viſit their tranſgreſſions with a rod, and their iniquity with ſtripes: And ſo</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.14. <hi>I will be his Father and he ſhall be my ſon, if he committ iniquity I will chaſtiſe him with the rod of men, and with the ſtripes of the children of men;</hi> So I ſay, though God cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe his own people with a rod, yet it is in meaſure, but the bones of the wicked ſhall be broken, it ſhall fall very heavy upon them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Though God doth viſit the tranſgreſſions of his people with a rod, yet it is in ſeaſon, it is but what is very ſeaſonable, they are ſo cut and lopt, as that they may grow again, Proverb. 13.24. <hi>He that ſpareth the rod, hateth his ſon, but he that loveth him chaſtneth him betimes,</hi> or in the morning, that is, he doth it in ſeaſon; but now the wicked are ſo cut off, that they never grow more;</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Though God viſiteth the tranſgreſſions of his people with a rod, yet his loving kindneſs he will never take away from them: <hi>If they ſin, ſaith God, I will viſit them with a rod, but my loving kindneſs I will not take away from them,</hi> Pſalm 89.33. But it is not ſo with the wicked.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Though God doth viſit the tranſgreſſions of his people with a rod, yet he will not ſuffer the rod to reſt upon their
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:57690:73"/>backs: if your Garments be dirty or duſty, you take a Rod or a wand, and beat out the duſt, but when it is out, you do not let the rod reſt upon the garment; ſo God cauſeth his rod to paſs upon his people, but when their dirt and filt is out and removed, he will take away the rod from off them, and will not ſuffer it to reſt upon their backs: So that you ſee there is a vaſt difference between the rod of the wicked and the rod of the Godly in theſe particulars; The rod of the wicked is a breaking rod: but the rod of the Godly is a correcting rod; The rod of the Godly is thrown into the fire, the rod of the wicked is not ſo; The rod of the godly is ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the rod of the wicked is not; the rod of the godly is in love, the rod of the wicked not ſo: And laſtly, God will not let the rod reſt upon the back of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but the rod of the wicked ſhall never be removed, and that is the ſecond propoſition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Gods Rod is a teaching rod, when God ſmites his people he deals with them in the way of the rod, and that is a teaching Rod, it brings a meſſage with it, For the cleering of this I ſhall ſhew you,</p>
            <p>Firſt, what thoſe leſſons are which the rod teacheth.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:57690:73"/>
            <p>Secondly, How this Rod teacheth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you ask what leſſons this rod teacheth: I anſwer in the General; the Rod teacheth the ſame Leſſon that the word teacheth, the rod teacheth no new Doctrine; but more particularly, the rod hath a leſſon for
<q>
                  <l>The Converted, and for</l>
                  <l>The Unconverted,</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, If you be unconverted, the rod calls upon you to turn to God: If a drunkard be ſick, the rod of ſickneſs ſayes, O Drunkard leave off thy Drunkenneſs, and turn to the Lord, this Leſſon the rod teacheth; and it taught the <hi>Jaylor,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Prodigal; when the rod of miſery and poverty was upon the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, why then ſaies he, <hi>I will return to my Father, for in my Fathers houſe is bread enough:</hi> Thus the rod teacheth the Unconverted to turn to the Lord; Art thou in thy ſins ſtill therefore, O poor ſinner, and haſt thou gone on a great while in thy ſins, and hath God warned thee often by his word to turn to him, and doth he now come upon thee with his rod? why this is all but to teach thee the ſame leſſon ſtill, though in another way,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:57690:74"/>and the leſſon is, <hi>Hear and your ſouls ſhall live, but if you will not hear the whipping, the correcting rod you ſhall hear,</hi> and feel the breaking, and the deſtroying rod; this is the leſſon which the rod teacheth the Unconverted,</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you be Converted,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The rod calls upon you to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie your ſins more and more, Proverbs 20.30. <hi>The blueneſs of a wound cleanſeth away evil, ſo do ſtripes the inward parts of the belly, Iſaiah</hi> 27.9. <hi>By this ſhall the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of Jacob be purged; by this,</hi> that is, by affliction, by the rod; if therefore you have neglected any duty, that you have performed heretofore, or ought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, the rod now calls upon you to do it now, <hi>Remember your firſt works and repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If you be Converted, the rod calls upon you to prize thoſe common mercies which you have not valued here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore; you have had peace but you have not prized it, now the rod of war ſhould teach you to prize it; you have had a quiet habitation, but you have not prized it, now the rod of Tumult calls upon you to prize your quiet habitation, and to be thankful for it; this is another leſſon which the rod teacheth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you be Converted, the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:57690:74"/>rod calls upon you to honour your own graces, Rom. 5.3. <hi>Knowing that tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion worketh patience, patience experience, experience hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed.</hi> You know how it is with a Countryman, that makes hay, the hay lies abroad, and he ſees a black cloud a coming, and he calls to his men to cock up and gather up the Hay; why look into the Nation, and ſee what a cloud is over us, this calls upon the people of God to gather up their Evidences: Here is a black cloud over us, O all ye people of God, gather up your evidences, that by the dark night of affliction, you may have light to read your own Graces; this is another leſſon the rod teacheth.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If you be Converted, the rod calls upon you to ſympathize with others in their Afflictions; by your own Afflictions you are called upon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate others in their Afflictions.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, and Laſtly, If you be converted, the rod calls upon you to provide for your great and laſt change: <hi>David</hi> underſtood this, and therefore he ſayes, <hi>Lord teach me ſo to number my dayes, that I may apply my heart to true wiſdom,</hi> Pſalm. 90.12.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the leſſons, which the rod teacheth.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:57690:75"/>
            <p>Secondly, If you would know further what the Rod teacheth; I anſwer Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively:</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Rod doth not teach you any ſkill or knowledge of its own, but the ſpirit of the Lord in the Rod that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that thou chaſtneſt, and teacheſt him out of thy law,</hi> Pſalm 94.12. By the Rod a man ſhall ſee that preſented to him, which lay hid before; when the glaſs is ſhaken you ſee that ſand, which you could hardly, or not at all perceive before; ſo when a man is ſhaken by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, his ſins are diſcovered to him; and a ſight of ſin is the firſt ſtep to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By the Rod you are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and broken, and made more fit and capable to receive inſtruction; when the young Horſe is once well broke, then he is afterwards fit for the ſaddle; now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions break men, and fit them for Gods ſervice, and for Gods work: If a narrow mouthed veſſel be in continual motion and unfixed, you cannot pour any liquor into it, you muſt firſt fix the veſſel, and then you may put what you will into it; ſo afflictions will fix you, and ſettle you, you have many a poor man, that no ground will hold him (as we uſe to ſay)
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:57690:75"/>till afflictions come, and then they ſettle him: If you ſow ſeed, you muſt firſt plow the ground, and then you ſow the ſeed; now what ſoul is there which doth not need Gods plow; why Gods Rod is his plow, and when this Rod comes and breaks, and humbles the heart, then it will receive the good ſeed of Gods word into the furrows of the heart; And further,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By the Rod a man will be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to lay hold of, and ſtick to thoſe promiſes, which he could not lay hold on before; for when the Rod comes and brings him low, the man is glad to run to the promiſe; and truly it is a very great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to us, that we have a promiſe to run unto, when we are brought low with the Rod; and thus you ſee what leſſons the Rod teacheth, and alſo how the Rod teacheth, it is a teaching Rod: And ſo I have done with the third propoſition, the next follows.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, As the Rod is teaching, and doth bring a meſſage with it; ſo this meſſage is ſent, eſpecially to the great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Towns of a Nation, or people, <hi>The Lords voice cryeth unto the City</hi> here in the Text; why, what City or Cities? It was <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Samariah;</hi> but did not
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:57690:76"/>Gods voice cry unto the leſſer Towns and Villages? Yes, but when a national Rod comes, the meſſage is eſpecially ſent to the great Towns, and Cities of a Nation. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Rod comes to avenge the Quarrel of the word; look therefore on that place, or people that have had the greateſt opportunities, as to hearing of the word, and having the means of grace, and yet have abuſed them; the greater controverſie hath the Rod with that place or people. Now great Towns, and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, have commonly the greateſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities as to the word and ordinances, and many times they are moſt abuſed in and by theſe; and therefore the voice of the Rod is eſpecially to great Towns, and Cities: <hi>Wo unto thee Capernaum,</hi> and why unto <hi>Capernaum,</hi> and not to the Towns and Villages? Why, <hi>Woe unto thee</hi> Capurnaum, <hi>for thou haſt been exalted unto Heaven,</hi> in regard of the means, and yet haſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented; <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.23. therefore woe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, above all the reſt of the Towns about thee: And ſo <hi>O</hi> Jeruſalem, Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I cannot but weep over thee; I would have gathered you but you would not,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore I cannot but weep over you; though the leſſer Towns
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:57690:76"/>and villages ſhall be deſtroyed, as well as the great ones; yet I weep not over them but over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for ſhe hath had the means of grace more abundantly, and yet hath not repented; and therefore I cannot but weep over it. When the Rod comes, I ſay, it comes more directly to the great Towns and Cities of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God will be ſure to puniſh thoſe that are the Ringleaders of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in a Nation: Now great Cities and Towns if they are not good, are ringlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to other Towns to do evil: Even as a great Oke, which drops upon the leſſer trees under him, ſpoils their growth, and corrupts them: And ſo if a man be rich, and not good, he drops upon others, and ſpoiles others: So I ſay, great Towns if not good, ſpoyl and corrupt the leſſer Towns and Villages; as if they be good, they are an help and an encouragement to others in goodneſs; therefore the Lords voice cryeth unto the Cities; and they ſhould all hear the rod, and who hath appointed it: that is the fourth propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The fifth and main followeth, that</p>
            <p>Fifthly, When the Lord doth viſit the tranſgreſſions of his people with a Rod, it is their true intereſt, and beſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:57690:77"/>to hear the Rod, and who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it.</p>
            <p>There are three things in this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>Firſt, When God doth viſit the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of his people with a Rod, it is their duty to hear what the Rod ſaith. And</p>
            <p>Secondly, Not only to hear what the rod ſaith, but alſo to conſider who hath appointed it. And</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is their true intereſt, and beſt wiſdom ſo to do.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not much inſiſt upon theſe. But for the firſt,</p>
            <p>Firſt, When the Lord doth viſit the tranſgreſſions of his people with a Rod, it is their duty to hear what the Rod ſaith; for as you hear, Gods Rod is a teaching Rod; and therefore when the Rod comes, it is your duty to lay your car cloſe to the rod, to hear what it ſays; for otherwiſe you will be found deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of its meſſage. If a King ſend his Ambaſſadour to ſpeak and treat with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he turns his ear from him, and will not hear him; why, will not he be found a deſpiſer of the meſſage? Now the Rod is a Meſſenger, an Ambaſſadour, and it comes from Heaven; if you will
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:57690:77"/>not hear it, you deſpiſe the meſſage of the Rod; not hearing is deſpiſing, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Rod comes, hear the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of it, <hi>my ſon deſpiſe not the chaſtening of the Almighty, ſaith</hi> Solomon, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.11.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is your duty to hear the Rod, and alſo to conſider who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it; not only to hear the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the Author alſo whereby the Rod is acted and guided: For</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thereby you will honour God in his diſpenſations: It was the ſpeech of Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> when the Souldiers broke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his houſe and plundred him, ſaith he, <hi>it is the Lord that hath taken them away;</hi> he did not ſay this thing they have taken away, and they have taken away ſuch, and ſuch things; no, he would not give them that honour; but as <hi>Job</hi> ſaid when the <hi>Sabeans</hi> took away his goods, <hi>the Lord gives, and the Lord takes away;</hi> ſo ſaid he, <hi>I will not honour them ſo much, as to ſay that they have taken away any thing from me, but the Lord hath done it;</hi> and thereby he gives God the honour of his diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and ſo muſt you, if you will hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By hearing the Rod, and who hath appointed it; you will much ſtrengthen your faith.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:57690:78"/>
            <p>Thirdly, By hearing the Rod, and who hath appointed it, you will be inabled to ſubmit ſweetly to the ſharp anger of Gods diſpenſations; <hi>I was dumb and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not my mouth, becauſe thou didſt it,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 39.9. So when <hi>Shimei</hi> curſed <hi>David,</hi> his ſervants would have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off his head, no ſaith <hi>David, Let him alone, it is the Lord that hath bidden him,</hi> 2 Sam. 16.11. Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> makes mention of a young man a Martyr, that when he was upon the Cart going to the fire; his Father who was a Papiſt, came out of his houſe, and would have beaten him, but the people hindring him; <hi>Pray</hi> ſaid he, <hi>let him alone, for he is my Father.</hi> So I ſay by hearing the Rod, and who hath appointed it, you will ſubmit unto the Lord, becauſe he is your Father.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, By hearing the Rod, and who hath appointed it, you will be led to prayer, and be brought to pray: Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer becomes a man or woman, when they are under the Rod: Pray tell me, when the child is whipt by his Father, doth the child fall down to the Rod, and beg of the Rod to ſpare him; no but he falls down to him, in whoſe hand the Rod is, to his Maſter, or his Father, and cries to him O ſpare me, pray ſpare me: So be
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:57690:78"/>not ſtubborn, but fall down to the Lord, when you are under the rod; and ſay, Lord ſpare me; do not ſay to the Rod ſpare me, do not cry to that when it is upon your backs; no, but ſee God, and obſerve his hand, and cry to him for help. But then</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As it is our duty to hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it; ſo it is alſo our true intereſt and beſt wiſdom to do it, becauſe it is the way to prevent further ſtrokes; when a child is under the Rod, and will not ſubmit; why ſays the Maſter, <hi>ſince you are ſo ſtout and ſo ſtubborn, I'le try who ſhall be Maſter, you or I;</hi> and ſo he ſtrikes on ſtill, till the child cries out I have done, why then ſays the Maſter I have done too: And thus it is with us, when we are under the Rod, if we be ſtubborn, and refuſe to hear the Rod of God, and who hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; well ſays God, <hi>I will try who ſhall be Maſter, you or I:</hi> what is the reaſon that ſome men go ſo long, ſo many years with the rod upon their backs; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not heard the Rod, and who hath appointed it; but now when a man ſhall ſay, <hi>Lord I have done,</hi> why then ſays God, <hi>I have done too, O ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:57690:79"/>
            <p>Beloved it is our beſt wiſdom, and our beſt courſe, to hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it.</p>
            <p>All that I ſhall ſay for Application, is this; It is our true intereſt, and beſt wiſdom, when the Rod comes, to hear the rod, and who hath appointed it, as hath been proved.</p>
            <p>O then that men were wiſe, and did underſtand it in this day. O England, England, the Rod is in thy ſtreets at this time, certainly there is a ſwinging Rod hangs over this Nation: O England what ſhall I ſay unto thee, but what the Prophet ſaith here; <hi>Hear ye the Rod, and who hath appointed it:</hi> O <hi>London</hi> Hear thou the Rod, and who hath appointed it, O <hi>Norwich</hi> Hear thou the Rod, and who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it, O <hi>Yarmouth</hi> hear thou the Rod, and who hath appointed it, for you ſhall thereby honour God, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then your own faith, you ſhall be able to keep ſilence in the evil day; you ſhall be made more fit to pray, and the rod will be ſooner removed from you. Therefore as you deſire that God may have the honour of all his diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and that your faith may be ſtrengthened, and that you may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to be ſilent in an evil day; then
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:57690:79"/>hear the rod, and who hath appointed it.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, what ſhall we do that we may hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it; we do confeſs that there is a ſmart Rod upon the back of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and upon the back of our families, but what ſhall we do that we may hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Firſt, Stand, and look upon the Rod, and you will find two things eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the Rod;
<list>
                  <item>1. Your Sin, and</item>
                  <item>2. Gods Deſign.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As for your ſin, look what ſin that is, which God holds before your face, before your conſcience, all the time he is ſtriking of you with the Rod, that is the ſin he ſtrikes you for. If a Dog worry a ſheep, you commonly go and beat the Dog in the face of the worried Sheep, that the Dog may thereby know and underſtand for what he is beaten: So when the Lord comes, and holds out one ſin for you to look on, eſpecially, then you may be ſure, the Rod comes upon you for that ſin.</p>
            <p>Again, Look what ſin that is, which doth naturally bring the Rod, that is the cauſe of it: As for example, If a man be
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:57690:80"/>drunk, and do thereby bring himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a feavor, will you not ſay that drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs was the cauſe of it?</p>
            <p>Again, Look what ſin that is, which is moſt like the Rod of all others, that ſin is that which brings the Rod; as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Suppoſe the Rod of this Nation be decay of Trading; may we not think, that ſome <hi>Stoln wedg of Gold</hi> is in this Nation, which is the cauſe of this Rod, becauſe it is like it: Or ſuppoſe the Rod of this Nation be, the Lords forſaking of it; may we not think that Apoſtacy is the cauſe of it, becauſe it is like it; therefore if you would hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it, then obſerve what ſin that is which is the cauſe of it. But</p>
            <p>Secondly, And ſo to conclude, as you are to look upon your ſin, ſo alſo upon Gods deſign in the Rod: Now God ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or never gives any mercy to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but he firſt brings them into the quite contrary condition; as for example, If God intends to give you great aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his love, he will firſt ſuffer you to fall into great Temptations, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he may thereby fit you for great aſſurance: Or if God intend to raiſe you to great honour in the world,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:57690:80"/>he will firſt ſuffer you to lie under ſome great reproach, that you may be thereby the more fit for your honour; And ſo, if God intend to fix, and ſettle a Nation, he will firſt ſuffer it, to come into great confuſion, and tumult, becauſe the Lord will thereby prepare that Nation, for the glorious ſettlement which he intends.</p>
            <p>How is it therefore with you? do you feel or ſee, the Rod of God upon this Nation, or upon your families, or upon the back of your own particular perſon? <hi>then hear ye the Rod, and who hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</hi> For Gods Rod is a teaching Rod, and it brings many leſſons with it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what I ſay to one, I ſay to all, and to my own ſoul alſo, <hi>Hear ye the Rod, and who hath appointed it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="sermon">
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:57690:81"/>
            <head>SERMON VII.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>AMOS 4.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Therefore thus will I do unto thee O Iſrael, and becauſe I will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God O Iſrael.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Chapter the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to pronounce ſome heavy Judgements againſt Gods own people Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, wherein there are three things moſt conſiderable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Judgement Threatned.</item>
               <item>2. The cauſe of the Judgement, and</item>
               <item>3. The Inference thereupon</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, The Judgement Threatned, and that is in the ſecond, and third verſes; <hi>The Lord hath ſworn by his holineſs, that to, the dayes ſhall come upon you, that he will take you away with hooks, and your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity with fiſh-hooks.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:57690:81"/>I will ſend Anglers among you, that ſhall pull you out of your houſes, as the little fiſhes are pulled out of the water; and then he goes on in the third verſe; <hi>And ye ſhall go out at the breaches ſaith the Lord,</hi> Though you be great and ſtrong yet will I make breaches among you ſaith the Lord, this is the Judgement threatned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Here is the cauſe of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that is therefold,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Oppreſſion, as at the firſt verſe, <hi>Hear this word ye kine of Baſhan, that are in the mountain of Samaria, which oppreſs the poor, which cruſh the needy, and ſo forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Another cauſe is Idolatry, and Superſtition; as at the 4. and 5. verſes, <hi>Come ye to Bethel, and tranſgreſs at Gilgal, multiply tranſgreſſion; Proclaim and publiſh the free offering, for this liketh you, O ye children of Iſrael ſaith the Lord God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The third cauſe is their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigableneſs, as at the 6. verſe, <hi>I have given you cleaneſs of Teeth in all your Cities, and want of bread in all your places, yet have ye not returned to me ſaith the Lord.</hi> And at the 7. verſe, <hi>And alſo I have with-holden rain from you, and I have cauſed it to rain upon one City, and not upon another City, ſo two or three Cities wandred unto one City to drink water, but they were not ſatisfied,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:57690:82"/>yet have ye not returned unto me ſaith the Lord,</hi> and at the 9. verſe, <hi>I have ſmitten you with blaſting and with mildew, when your gardens, and your vineyards, and your figtrees, and your olive trees increaſed, the palmer worm devoured them, yet have ye not returned unto me ſaith the Lord,</hi> and at the 10. verſe, <hi>I have ſent among you the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, after the manner of Egypt, your young men have I ſlain with the ſword, and have taken away your horſes, and I have made the ſtink of your camps, to come up unto your noſtrils, yet have ye not returned unto me ſaith the Lord,</hi> and at the 11. verſe, <hi>I have overthrown ſome of you, as God overthrew Sodom, and Gomorrah, and ye were as a firebrand pluckt out of the burning, yet have ye not returned unto me ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Therefore by way of Inference he concludes;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore this will I do unto thee O Iſrael, and becauſe I will do this unto thee, prepare to neet thy God O Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words you have a double In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference which God makes,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Therefore thus will I do unto thee, I have been a long time ſtriving with you (as if he ſhould ſay) and I have been at a ſtand whether I ſhould puniſh you or not, yet have ye not returned
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:57690:82"/>unto me, therefore now I am reſolved, <hi>thus will I do unto thee.</hi> And then</p>
            <p>Secondly, Now I am reſolved, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to meet thy God O Iſrael, therefore do thou prepare to meet thy God O Iſrael: I do not ſend you a challeng ſaith God, that you ſhould prepare to meet with your God to fight with him, or to reſiſt him, not to meet God in his anger, and to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him, no; but prepare to meet thy God, by preventing his Judgements, with your Repentance, and returning unto him. If a man be coming to your houſe, and you go out to meet him, why then you prevent him by meeting of him; So when we prevent Gods Judgements, by our Repentance, we are ſaid to meet with God.</p>
            <p>From hence then I take up this Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Doctrine.</p>
            <p>That when God is reſolved to come out againſt a Nation or people, it is their duty to prepare to meet with God.</p>
            <p>For the opening and proſecuting hereof I ſhall labour to ſhew you,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That God doth ſeem ſometimes to be at a ſtand concerning a people, whether he ſhould truſt to them any longer or not, or whether he ſhould puniſh them or not.</p>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:57690:83"/>
            <p>Secondly, That if they do not come to him, and meet with him, he will then reſolve to go out againſt them in his wrath.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That when God doth reſolve to go out againſt a people in his wrath, it is their duty to prepare to meet him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſhall labour to ſhew, how a people, or family, or perſon, may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelves to meet with God in the way of his anger, when he is going out againſt them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Though God is alwaies reſolved in himſelf what to do with a people, yet he ſeems to us to be at a ſtand, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould deliver them or not, or whether he ſhould puniſh them or not, whether he ſhould ſhew mercy to them or not; as you may ſee Exod. 33.5. <hi>For the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſay unto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ye are a ſtiffnecked people; I will come up into the midſt of thee in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſume thee; therefore now put off thy Ornaments from thee, that I may know what to do unto thee,</hi> that I may ſhew, or make known what to do unto thee, as it is in the Hebrew: this is ſpeaking after the manner of men; and ſo in Gen. 18.21. <hi>I will go down now, and ſee whether they
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:57690:83"/>have done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come unto me, and if not, I will know:</hi> And Again, Gen. 22.12. <hi>Lay not thine hand upon the Lad, neither do any thing unto him, for now I know that thou feareſt God;</hi> ſpeaking after the manner of men. And Again, Hoſea 6.4. <hi>O</hi> Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im <hi>what ſhall I do unto thee, O</hi> Judah <hi>what ſhall I do unto thee;</hi> And in Hoſea 11.8. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up O</hi> Ephraim, <hi>how ſhall I deliver thee</hi> Iſrael, <hi>how ſhall I make thee as</hi> Admah, <hi>how ſhall I ſet thee as</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boim: Here are four Hows in our Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, though but two in the Hebrew, <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, How ſhall I deliver thee, How ſhall I make thee as</hi> Admah. <hi>How ſhall I ſet thee as</hi> Zeboim: As if the Lord, (to ſpeak after the manner of men) were in a great ſtreight, and knew not what to do, was not reſolved what to do; So I ſay though God is alwaies reſolved in himſelf, yet he ſeems to us to be at a ſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, whether he ſhall ſhew mercy or no.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, how doth this come to paſs, that God doth ſometimes ſeem to be thus at a ſtand.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, you know how it is with a tender Father, that hath a rebellious Child; ſaith the Father, I will thruſt him
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:57690:84"/>out of doors, I will utterly caſt him off, I have often admoniſhed him, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him, and corrected him, and yet he is never the better, therefore I am reſolved even to turn him out of doors; I but then he reflects, and thinks again, He is my child, he is the Son of my bowels, how ſhall I, how can I give him up, how can I turn him out of doors? why now God is more tender to his Children, than any Father can be to his Children, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his being at a ſtand doth ſpeak out, and declare his bowels to his people: His bowels are at work whilſt their ſins pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him; One while he looks upon their ſins, and another while he looks upon Chriſts ſatisfaction; one while he hears the Law call Juſtice, Juſtice, another while he hears Chriſt cry Mercy, Mercy; There is Juſtice and mercy both in God, that he may have the honour of both, and therefore God ſeems to be at a ſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; ſaies God, Theſe are my people, and if I puniſh them the enemies will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach me, and I ſhall be diſhonoured, and they are my people ſtill for all their ſinning againſt me, and thus God ſeems to be at a ſtand.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, when may God ſeem to be at a ſtand, and not to be reſolved
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:57690:84"/>what to do, ſpeaking after the manner of men.</p>
            <p>I anſwer firſt, when the Saints and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God, know not what is beſt to be done in regard of the times, then is God at a ſtand, For ſaith the Lord, <hi>ſhall I do any thing, and not reveal it to my ſervants the Prophets:</hi> Therefore I ſay when the Saints, and Servants, and Miniſters of God are at a ſtand, and know not what to do, then God ſeems to be at a ſtand.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When the Diſpenſations of God, go forward, and backward, then the Lord ſeems to be at a ſtand; when a man goes out of his houſe about his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and goes forward and backward in the ſtreet, you will ſay, that man is not well reſolved what to do, nor which way to go; And thus it ſeems to be ſometimes with God, his dipenſations in the world go forward, and backward, and this is the time, that God is, as it were at a ſtand, whether he ſhall ſhew mercy or no; And ſo I have done with the firſt general.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is this: That though God ſeem to be at a ſtand ſometimes, yet if men do not come unto him, and meet him. He will reſolve to go forth againſt them, <hi>Therefore thus will I do unto thee:</hi> I have been a long time ſtriving with you, and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:57690:85"/>yet have ye not returned unto me, and now I am reſolved, and this is Gods Meſſage.</p>
            <p>Now for the cleering of this</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall open the truth of it unto you.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall prove it, and</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall ſhew you, when God may be ſaid to go forth againſt a people or Nation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For opening of it, you muſt not think, as I ſaid before, that God is at any time unreſolved in himſelf, or that he knows not what to do, No, <hi>For known to God are all his works from the beginning of the world,</hi> unto the end ſaies the Apoſtle. Acts 15.18. There is nothing future, or to come, to God; God is not meaſured, neither doth he meaſure by time; There is nothing before, nor after with God in Eternity; All is preſent, and altogether before him at once, and therefore I ſay God is not at any time unreſolved in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, what he ſhall do with this or that people. Now further, God is ſaid to will a thing in a twofold reſpect, either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<list>
                  <item>Of his Decree, or</item>
                  <item>Of his Diſpenſations.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In regard of his decree, his love is
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:57690:85"/>from Eternity, and yet the ſame man may ſeem to be a child of wrath in regard of the diſpenſation: every Elect perſon is a child of God from Eternity in regard of Gods decree, and yet he is a child of wrath until he be converted in regard of Gods diſpenſations. So when I ſay, that God ſeems to be at a ſtand, and unreſolved, and that if men do not come unto him he will then go forth againſt them: This is not to be underſtood in regard of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, but in regard of his diſpenſations. But</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the proof of it: it is ſaid, God <hi>will not alwayes ſtrive with the Children</hi> of men, neither will he alwayes wait, and expect fruit from a fruitles and barren people, Read the parable of the figtree Luke 13.7. <hi>A certain man had a figtree &amp;c. and he ſaid unto the dreſſer of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard, behold theſe three years I come, ſeeking fruit on this figtree, and find none, cut it down why cumbreth it the ground.</hi> Now though this parable doth concern the Jews, and it concerns us alſo, wherein we may ſee there are three times, which go over the heads of all thoſe that ſit under the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:57690:86"/>
            <list>
               <item>A time of ſoul mercy.</item>
               <item>A time of Gods forbearance, and</item>
               <item>A time of Judgement or cutting down.</item>
            </list>
            <p>There is time of forbearance and ſtriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a time when God ſeems to be at a ſtand, but then if men will not come unto him, he will reſolve to go forth againſt them. Rom. 2.4, 5. <hi>verſes. Deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his goodneſs, and forbearance, and long ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſs of God leadeth thee to repentance; But after thy hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and impenitent heart, treaſureſt up unto thy ſelf wrath againſt the day of wrath, and revelation of the righteous Judgement of God, who will render to every man according to his deeds.</hi> So I ſay that, though God ſeem to be at a ſtand as to his diſpenſations, yet if men do not come in unto him, he will then reſolve to go forth againſt them in his wrath.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay further, when may God be ſaid to go forth againſt a Nation or people in his anger.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For anſwer you may know it by Gods diſpenſations, if his diſpenſations do beſpeak ſo much, and do plainly declare that God is going forth againſt a Nation or people, then you may be ſure that he is
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:57690:86"/>reſolved to go forth in his anger: and therefore</p>
            <p>Firſt, Obſerve when a Judgement comes that is extraordinary, then the Lord is gone out againſt that people: <hi>The Lord is known by the Judgements, which he executeth, the wicked is ſnared in the work of his own hands, Pſal.</hi> 9.16.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Look when God reſtrains prayer from a people, when he knocks off, and draws off the hearts of his children from praying for ſuch a people, then is God certainly come out againſt them in his wrath.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, When all things work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the worſt, then the Lord is againſt that people; when all things inſtead of working together for the beſt, do the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and work together for the worſt, then is God ſurely againſt that people.</p>
            <p>But then 2. As you may know when God is reſolved to go out againſt a people by his diſpenſations, ſo you may alſo know it by our Practices: As when God afflicts a people for crying Sins, and yet incorrigableneſs follows, then doth the Lord reſolve to, go againſt that people in wrath: As you may ſee in this Chapter wherein our Text is, There you find the people were guilty of great ſins, of great
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:57690:87"/>oppreſſion, and great ſuperſtition, and Idolatry, and God did not only afflict them for theſe ſins but for others too, and therefore you find in the 7. verſe, <hi>I have with held the rain from you, and have cauſed it to rain upon one City, and not upon another,</hi> Here was diſtinction of Judgments accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſeveral ſins: And ſo at the 11. verſe. <hi>I have overthrown you, as God overthrew Sodom, and Gomorrah, and you were as firebrands pluckt out of the burning,</hi> &amp;c. God exerciſed them with ſeveral Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and they were <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions too, and yet they were incorriga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; God tells them, that he had afflicted them with cleaneſs of teeth, and want of rain, <hi>and yet have they not returned unto me ſaith the Lord, therefore thus will I do unto thee,</hi> &amp;c. Thus you ſee what diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing afflictions they were exerciſed with, <hi>I have ſent the Peſtilence among you, yet have ye not returned unto me ſaith the Lord;</hi> and yet after all theſe ſore ſtrokes, they ſtill remained incorrigable, and therefore God was reſolved to go forth againſt them in his wrath, and ſo I have done with the ſecond General.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is the duty of a people, or Nation to prepare to meet the Lord, when he is coming out againſt them:
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:57690:87"/>
               <hi>Therefore thus will I do unto thee O Iſrael, and becauſe I will do thus, prepare to meet thy God O Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the cleering of this I ſhall endeavour to ſhew you;</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it is a dreadful thing to meet with God in the way of his anger, and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That though it be dreadful, yet it is not ſo dreadful to the people of God as to others.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That though it be not ſo dreadful to the people of God as to others, yet it is very uncomfortable for them too, to meet with God in his wrath.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That when God is gone forth againſt a people in his anger, and in the way of his wrath, it is their duty to prepare to meet with God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is a very dreadful thing to meet with God in the way of his anger, <hi>who may abide the day of his wrath? It is a fearful thing</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>to fall into the hand of the living God,</hi> Heb. 10.31. <hi>For our God is a conſumming fire,</hi> Heb. 12.29. not a warming fire: There is a warming fire in your houſes, and that is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable in cold weather, but there is a conſuming fire alſo, a fire that burns down houſes, and Cities, and that fire is very
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:57690:88"/>terrible and dreadful: why our God is a conſuming fire; your fire conſumes your wood and coal, but it doth not conſume your houſe, it doth not remove the Rocks: but the fire of Gods anger doth ſo, as you may ſee, Nahum. 1.5, 6. verſes. <hi>The mountains quake at him, the hills melt, and the earth is burnt at his preſence, yea the world, and all that dwell therein; who can ſtand before his indignation, and who can abide the fierceneſs of his anger, his fury is poured out like fire, and the rocks are thrown down by him.</hi> Thus you ſee it is a very dreadful thing to meet with God in the way of his anger. But</p>
            <p>Secondly, Though it be dreadful and terrible, yet it is not ſo dreadful to the people of God as to others.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Though God be angry with his own people; yet it is but little, in compariſon to what he is with others; As in Zach. 1.2. <hi>The Lord was ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with your Fathers,</hi> and at the 12. verſe, <hi>there it is ſaid God had indignation againſt them threeſcore and ten years,</hi> and then at the 15. verſe, <hi>And I am very ſore diſpleaſed with the Heathen that are at eaſe, for I was but a little diſpleaſed, and they helped forward the affliction:</hi> Here you ſee God was greatly diſpleaſed with the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:57690:88"/>Heathen, and but little diſpleaſed againſt his people; his diſpleaſure is but little to them, in compariſon with what it is to others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Though God be angry with his own people, yet his anger is their friend. If a man be my friend, not only his purſe is my friend, but his ſword alſo, if I have occaſion; ſo if God be my friend, not only his love is my friend, but his anger too, but it is not ſo with the wicked.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Though God be angry with his own people yet they have alwayes free grace to fly unto, and to be their friend, but it is not thus with the wicked.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Though God be angry with his own people, yet they know, or may know, that God is in Covenant with them, and that they have ſome ſweet, and precious promiſes which belong to them: Nahum. 1.5, 6. <hi>Who can abide the fierceneſs of his wrath,</hi> &amp;c. But look at the 7. verſe. <hi>The Lord is good, a ſtrong hold in the day of trouble, and he knoweth them that truſt in him:</hi> in the worſt times the people of God have promiſes to run unto for ſhelter; mark how the promiſe comes in here: Having ſhewed the fierceneſs of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:57690:89"/>Gods wrath in the 5. and 6. verſes, <hi>who can ſtand before his preſence,</hi> &amp;c. He comes in with this promiſe at the 7. verſe, The Lord is good, and a ſtrong hold in the day of trouble, he knoweth them that truſt in him.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Though God be angry with, and afflict his own people, yet they know, or may know, that God is afflicted with them, Chriſt partakes in their Afflictions with them.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Though God do afflict his own people for their ſins, yet they know or may know, that God alwayes gives a due allowance in reference to their ſins and Infirmities; the beſt Gold muſt have an allowance of ſome droſs, and the beſt Saint muſt have an allowance upon the Account of his Infirmities, ſaies the Lord, Hoſea 11.8. <hi>How ſhall I make thee as Admah, and ſet thee as Zeboim;</hi> why did not the Lord ſay; How ſhall I make thee as Sodom or Gomorrah, <hi>ſayes Jerom,</hi> It was becauſe Admah, and Zeboim were leſſer Cities, and were drawn into ſin, by the example of the great Cities of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Gomorrah: and ſo the ten Tribes were drawn into ſin, by the great Cities of Judah, and by Jeruſalem, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſaies, how ſhall I make thee as
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:57690:89"/>Admah, &amp;c. So I ſay, God doth alwayes give an allowance to his own people, even in the day of his wrath.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Though God be angry with his own people, yet they may ſee God ſmile ſometimes, even through his frowns; faith doth many times pull the vizard from the face of Chriſt as I may ſay, that when he ſeems to be their enemy, yet ſtill they know that all things ſhall work together for their good.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Though God be angry with his own people, yet they know, or may know, that God will alwayes have a hiding place for them, and ſo he will never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for others. It may be obſerved, that when Gods people in former Times were perſecuted in one part of the world, they had alwayes acceptance and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintment in ſome other part of the world; and when they were perſecuted from thence, they had ſtill acceptance elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, according to that of Chriſt, <hi>If they perſecute you in one City, flee unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, until the Son of Man come, Matt.</hi> 10.23. Why what is the meaning of this, but that God will alwayes have ſome hiding place for his people, until Chriſt come again.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, Though God be angry with
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:57690:90"/>his own people, yet they know or may know, that they are delivered from wrath to come, and they may comfort them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thus; Tis true, that this diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God towards me is in anger, but yet I am delivered from wrath to come; but now it is not ſo with others, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſpenſations of Gods wrath upon the wicked, are but fore-runners of his eternal wrath, which ſhall come upon them; but it is not ſo with the Saints. And ſo I conclude this ſecond particular, That though it be very dreadful when God goes forth againſt a people in his wrath, yet it is not ſo dreadful to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God as it is to others. But</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Though it be not ſo terrible for the people of God to meet with God in his anger and as it is for others, yet it is a very hard and uncomfortable thing for them to meet with God in this way, for they are uſed to have other kind of meetings with God, they uſe to meet him in the Aſſemblies, to meet him in love, there the Saints deſire to meet with God. But</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If God do go forth againſt a people in his wrath, it is their duty, the duty of them all, and of Gods own people alſo, to go forth to meet God: It is here commanded in the Text by way
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:57690:90"/>of reaſon; It is the duty of Gods people and of others alſo, to honour God when they are under his diſpenſations; now when men go forth to meet God, then they honour him; <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> intended to honour the Angel, and therefore they went forth to meet him; <hi>Joſeph</hi> would honour his Father <hi>Jacob,</hi> and therefore he went forth to meet him: <hi>Moſes</hi> would honour his Father <hi>Jethro,</hi> and therefore he went forth to meet him: <hi>Abigail</hi> would honour <hi>David,</hi> and therefore ſhe went forth to meet him; <hi>Martha</hi> would honour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and therefore went forth to meet him; <hi>Cornelius</hi> and the believing Romans would honour <hi>Paul,</hi> and therefore they went forth to meet him: And ſo if a man be coming to your houſe, if you would honour him you go forth to meet him; Why now it is our duty to honour God, and therefore it is our duty alſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to meet with God, that we may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by honour him.</p>
            <p>And further It is the duty of all Gods people to hold a compliance with his diſpenſations, now if you do not go to meet with God, you do not comply with his diſpenſations: So that I ſay when God comes forth againſt a people, it is their
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:57690:91"/>duty to go forth, and to prepare to meet him. And ſo I come to the fourth General which was propoſed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If it be the duty of a people, when God goes forth againſt them in his anger to prepare to meet him, Why then what ſhall we do, to prepare our ſelves to meet with God; for ſometimes God ſeems to be at a ſtand, and to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolved what to do, and ſometimes he is reſolved to go forth againſt a people, now what ſhall we do that we may prepare to meet God in both theſe Caſes.</p>
            <p>I ſhall anſwer theſe two Queſtions, and ſpeak to them diſtinctly, and ſo conclude without any further Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you would meet with God in this caſe, then break off from your uncertainties and leave them, do not ſtand ſhall I, ſhall I, as we ſay, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to your repentance and newneſs of life, be not uncertain in your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and practices. As in Hoſea 6.4. <hi>O Ephraim ſaith God what ſhall I do unto thee, why Lord,</hi> might they ſay, <hi>Why art thou at an uncertainty with us, why ſaith God, becauſe you are at an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:57690:91"/>with me, your goodneſs is as the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away:</hi> Sometimes you take up good reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, but they fade away again pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently; Sometimes you are grieved and troubled for ſin, but your repentance fades way, as the morning dew; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you will perform duties, but your goodneſs fades away quickly, and therefore I am at this uncertainty with you, becauſe you are at ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty with me; would you then meet with God in this caſe, why then break off from your uncertainties, that is the firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If God ſeem to be at a ſtand, then do you repent and turn to God, for this is that which God expects, and looks for, <hi>yet have ye not returned unto me ſaith the Lord:</hi> The Lord repeats it again and again, in the cloſe of ſeveral verſes, though I have been at a ſtand, yet have ye not returned unto me ſaith the Lord. Therefore I ſay when God ſeems to be at a ſtand, be ſure that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto God; and what I ſay unto one, I ſay unto all, and to my own ſoul alſo; Doth the Lord ſeem to be at a ſtand with us, then let us all return to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:57690:92"/>the Lord by repentance, it may be he ſtaies his hand to ſee what we will do.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If God ſeem to be at a ſtand, and if you would meet with him, then go, and make your choice, <hi>Chuſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, If the Lord ſeem to be at an uncertainty in point of his diſpenſations, and if you would meet with God, then take heed that you do not deſire the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day, take heed that there be none among you who do deſire the wofull day to come: A day of confuſion in a Nation is a wofull day, a day of civil War is a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day, civil War begins with uncivil ſins, and ends in uncivil Butcheries. Again</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If God ſeem to be at a ſtand, in point of his diſpenſations, and if Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations do then come to draw you off from God, why do you anſwer all with this: How ſhall I do this thing, and yet not ſin againſt God, how ſhall I do this thing, and yet not ſin againſt my own conſcience, ſhall the Lord have his <hi>How's</hi> for you as I may ſay, and will you
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:57690:92"/>have none for him? ſhall the Lord ſay, How ſhall I give thee up, <hi>O England!</hi> How ſhall I give thee up; <hi>O London!</hi> How ſhall I give thee up, <hi>O Yarmouth!</hi> and will not you ſay, How ſhall I ſin againſt the Lord, ſhall the Lords bowels yearn, and turn within him for you, and ſhall not you turn to God; ſhall the Lord ſay, O Drunkard! How ſhall I give thee up? O Swearer! How ſhall I give thee up? O Sabbath-breaker! how ſhall I give thee up? O unclean Perſon or the like, how ſhall I give thee up? And ſhall not you ſay how ſhall I do this thing, and yet not ſin againſt God? Therefore do thus, and then you will be able to meet with God in this caſe.</p>
            <p>But 2. As for the ſecond part of this Queſtion. Suppoſe the Lord be reſolved as I hope he is not, to go forth againſt this Nation, you may obſerve how he ſtands hovering as it were over the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but if God ſhould reſolve to go out againſt us, would you know how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to meet with God?</p>
            <p>Then you muſt obſerve what thoſe evils are that do provoke God, and labour and ſtrive againſt them till they be removed; and in order hereunto,</p>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:57690:93"/>
            <p>Firſt, If you would meet with God in the way of his Juſtice and Anger, then you muſt get Chriſt into your Arms, as I may ſay, and ſo go forth and meet God: It is written of one, that when he would gain favour of his King, he uſe to get the Kings ſon in his Arms, and ſo he got the favour he deſired; ſo if you would find favour with God, get Jeſus Chriſt into your arms, and ſo go forth to meet him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you would meet with God in the way of his anger and Juſtice, then you muſt humble your ſelf before him and ſubmit unto him: There are two parts in Humiliation, Sorrow for ſin, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to God; now it may be you are wanting in one of theſe, therefore labour to abound in both, and ſo go forth to meet God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you would meet with God in the way of his anger and Juſtice, then do you live juſtly, and deal juſtly and righteouſly. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee O man what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God;</hi> Micah. 6.8. O my friends, labour to do what God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and what God expects: Now when he comes out againſt a people in the
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:57690:93"/>way of his Juſtice, he expects that they ſhould be found doing Juſtice; read the 9. verſe, <hi>The Lords voice cryeth unto the City, Hear ye the rod, and who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it;</hi> Gods voice is to ſcare us, and to cauſe us to leave ſin and to turn unto him, and therefore he ſayes, Hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If you would meet with God in the way of his anger, then preſent unto God your free-will offerings, and pray unto him and ſeek his face; when <hi>Jacob</hi> went forth to meet his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> he ſent preſents to him, and his brothers face was changed; O what will become of thoſe that never prayed one prayer more in private for all this anger and wrath of God, that ſeems to be coming out againſt us.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If you would meet with God in his anger, then get ſuffering grace: How can you be able to meet with God in the way of his anger in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Times, if you have not ſuffering grace?</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If you would meet with God in his anger, be ſure to be doing the work of your preſent day; ſhew mercy
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:57690:94"/>to thoſe that want mercy, They that are merciful ſhall obtain mercy with God; what will your money avail you in the day of Gods wrath? The only way to meet with God in his wrath, is to ſhew mercy.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, If you would be able to meet with God in the way of his anger, then wait upon God in the way of his Judgements, and in due time you ſhall be able to ſay, This is our God, <hi>Loe this our God we have waited for him;</hi> and if God be going, lay hold of him, take hold upon him, for ſo we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, Haiah 27.4, 5. <hi>Fury is not in me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Or let him take hold of my ſtrength that he may make peace with me, and he ſhall make peace with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eighthly, If you would meet with God in the way of his anger, then lay aſide your particular Intereſts, and think it your duty, and deſire to do it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If you would prepare to meet with God in the way of his anger, then now whilſt you have a little time, Goe and ſet your ſelf and your houſe in order, that whatſoever may come, you may have nothing
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:57690:94"/>elſe to do but to dye; And then if God do come in Judgement, and Anger, you may be able to ſay I have heard the Rod, and have trembled, and have prepared to meet with God: And if God ſhould not come in wrath, but ſome other way, yet you will have great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in your preparing to meet with God; For either God will come out againſt the Nation in anger, or he will not; if he do not, you will not loſe by your preparing to meet him; but if he do, and you are prepared to meet with him, then will God meet with you in Love, becauſe you have prepared to meet with him in Anger.</p>
            <p>Therefore as you deſire to be found doing the work, that God would have you to do in this Caſe, Think of, and remember what hath been ſpoken. All you that hear this word of God, prepare to meet with God, you know not how ſoon the Lord may come out againſt you in wrath, his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations in the world ſeem to run backward, and forward: Therefore
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:57690:95"/>be alwayes ready, and prepared to meet with God, which way ſoever he may come, according to this of our Text,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus will I do unto thee O Iſrael, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will do thus unto thee, prepare to meet thy God O Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>INIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="docket_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:57690:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57690:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Bridgs ſeven Sermons.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57690:96"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
